[SPEAKER_20]: to accept those into the record?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yes, here.
[SPEAKER_20]: I get a commission to motion them into the record.
[SPEAKER_20]: To accept the minutes from the August special meeting.
[SPEAKER_21]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_20]: Seconded.
[SPEAKER_20]: Second by Commissioner McGiven, I'll have a roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastorow?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner Buckley?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, by nothing, they have been approved.
[SPEAKER_20]: and approved into the record.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner McGibbon, you have a motion you suggested you'd like to make before we begin new business?
[SPEAKER_15]: Yes, can I make a motion to take item 2022-49 out of order?
[SPEAKER_15]: You can, commissioners for discussion a second.
[SPEAKER_08]: Second.
[SPEAKER_21]: Just a question, are we moving it up?
[SPEAKER_21]: Is that what the?
[SPEAKER_16]: Yeah, it's the permit parking program for GLX increased to half a mile.
[SPEAKER_21]: Just move it all the way up to the front.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is that what we're doing?
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is this one going to take a while like the last discussion?
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_21]: I just, I asked because it seems like there are a lot of people on here for some individual business that may have to wait a while if we take long like we did last time.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think one of the concerns, while this is up for discussion is that I know I myself have to be at the city council meeting at 7pm, but I have the ability to have Sergeant Rogers step in my place or Sergeant McGilvery step in my place but do I don't know if the two other commissioners have to be at the city council tonight.
[SPEAKER_08]: I do as well.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't have to be there at seven sharp, but I just wondered if we could, if the other items, we could knock a bunch of them off quickly and that would move this through this pretty quickly because this item could take the whole two hours and then we won't ever get to the rest of the business.
[SPEAKER_21]: I agree.
[SPEAKER_21]: Tim, could you wait, let's do a three or four of these and see where we are.
[SPEAKER_21]: And then if we need to slide it up, I'll entertain that motion.
[SPEAKER_16]: That's okay with me.
[SPEAKER_16]: I think I, I like the idea of that motion that I made just because I agree with folks who might take a while I get it definitely be up by seven to City Council.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, so there, there is a motion but I think one of the commissioners asking if you'd rescind the motion before we second it.
[SPEAKER_16]: Well I don't know.
[SPEAKER_16]: Let's see who else do we have on here I mean I don't know if
[SPEAKER_16]: what other folks think it's, we got Alicia, we got Steve.
[SPEAKER_08]: Do we have to finish that tonight?
[SPEAKER_08]: I mean, I just, I'd like to get, knock a bunch of these requests for handicap signs and stuff.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm wondering if some of these have been waiting.
[SPEAKER_16]: All right.
[SPEAKER_16]: Is any, are there, let's put it this way.
[SPEAKER_16]: Are there any other commission members that, um, support what I propose?
[SPEAKER_16]: I mean, I'm, I'm fine with rescinding it and trying a few.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, let's just resolve with this.
[SPEAKER_20]: May I have a call on, uh, well, we don't have a second.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, and we didn't.
[SPEAKER_20]: We can see if there's a second.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yep, Commissioner Pesetoro, you're the only one who hasn't weighed in on this.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, I'll second.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right, so second to take 2022-49 out of order, I'll run the roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner McGibbon?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: No.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pesetoro?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_20]: No.
[SPEAKER_22]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, on the three to two the motion carries 2022-49.
[SPEAKER_20]: Let's see if we can get through this in quick time given the extended agenda we have 2022-49 expansion of the pilot residential permit parking opt out program.
[SPEAKER_20]: by the GLX stations.
[SPEAKER_20]: There's a list of public streets that has been proposed.
[SPEAKER_20]: Rather than me read this long agenda, I think I'm going to turn it over to Todd Blake.
[SPEAKER_20]: Todd, could you give us your presentation this evening on this item of business?
[SPEAKER_32]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_32]: I'm going to share the screen here.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, for those who weren't at the August meeting, the city's trying to take a proactive approach to addressing parking issues that may arise.
[SPEAKER_33]: One of the main reasons is that may arise when the green light stations, open.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, but besides the green light stations I do want to touch upon.
[SPEAKER_33]: That doesn't mean there aren't any other parking issues that currently exist in South Medford hillside, and that's why many of the streets are already parent parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: So the Greenland extension stations opening is just the last straw that, you know, pushed us to take a more proactive approach.
[SPEAKER_33]: So instead of waiting for each individual.
[SPEAKER_33]: street to propose to have current parking individually.
[SPEAKER_33]: We're trying to rip the bandaid off fast and suggested for the, these larger areas, and then still allow folks that do not want current parking the ability to get a petition to opt out essentially.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, the blue line on this map represents what was approved at the August meeting a special August meeting, meaning streets within that blue line that didn't already have current parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: were approved to have permit parking except the private streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we're talking about public streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: And now at this meeting, based on some comments received at the August meeting, as well as follow-up comments received, it seemed like streets beyond the blue border were concerned and they wanted permit parking as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we're taking the initial, the additional step to expand the region
[SPEAKER_33]: to now include the red border.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, all public streets that don't currently have current parking would be approved for current parking negating the need for all the residents that want on those streets to have a petition to get current parking, but still allowing the ability to streets in that area to get a petition to opt out or remove the parent parking, if it goes forward tonight.
[SPEAKER_33]: That's the shortest gist of it.
[SPEAKER_33]: I believe that covers it, but feel free to...
[SPEAKER_33]: ask questions by the commission or the community, the community for it, it does encompass a lot more streets than the last version.
[SPEAKER_33]: So there are about 110 streets or so in the red border that weren't included in the blue border previously.
[SPEAKER_33]: And about half of them are already parent parking about half the public streets already from parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: So this would cover the remaining public streets in that border between the blue and the red on the screen.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it really is intended to help folks in the area, proactively, avoid additional parking issues or concerns.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that in the concentric circles that you see here are quarter mile radius and then a half mile race from those stations, and I know in the robocalls it did say for the blue border.
[SPEAKER_33]: about a quarter mile, and this one may be about half mile.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's plus or minus, you know, once you, once you map out the streets that it covers, it makes sense to include a whole street versus half a street.
[SPEAKER_33]: That's why the blue border came about and now the red border.
[SPEAKER_33]: So in some areas it might be as much as three quarters.
[SPEAKER_33]: of a mile away from the Greenline station.
[SPEAKER_33]: But once you do the whole area to leave a couple of streets here and there didn't make much sense.
[SPEAKER_33]: And usually if you're the one remaining street, you might experience issues.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that's the methodology behind it.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's meant to help and be in a proactive way versus a reactive way.
[SPEAKER_29]: Hello, can somebody hear me?
[SPEAKER_29]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_33]: We can hear you.
[SPEAKER_20]: If we can hear you, we're presenting an item from the agenda.
[SPEAKER_29]: I'm sorry, I'm so sorry.
[SPEAKER_29]: I just wasn't sure what was going on.
[SPEAKER_29]: I was told to sign in at five o'clock, so.
[SPEAKER_20]: Oh, you're signed in, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: We're going to have public participation in a moment and we'll get to you at that point, thank you.
[SPEAKER_29]: Okay, so I have a bus that I'm supposed, I'm at the JFK Federal Building.
[SPEAKER_29]: I have a bus, well, nevermind, I missed it.
[SPEAKER_29]: So I'll just wait.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right, thank you.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we're just about done anyways.
[SPEAKER_33]: One, you know, a couple further clarifications is that
[SPEAKER_33]: The proposal is to be permanent park and only 24 six meaning 24 hours a day, six days a week so it excludes Sundays and holidays.
[SPEAKER_33]: Other points of note, or that's that's along all residential.
[SPEAKER_08]: Todd you got muted.
[SPEAKER_08]: Everybody did Todd we can't hear you.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, sorry.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so some additional notes or this is supposed to be 24 six so six days a week, 24 hours a day to exclude Sundays and holidays.
[SPEAKER_33]: And that's a long residential uses.
[SPEAKER_33]: If it's on a major street like a main street saying there are a lot of businesses or non residential uses.
[SPEAKER_33]: The proposal is to have to our parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: 8am to 8pm, except by permit and then permit overnight from 8pm to 8am.
[SPEAKER_33]: And another important notice these changes only apply to.
[SPEAKER_33]: areas that are currently unrestricted on those public streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, if there are areas on those public streets that have no parking zones or 30 minute area.
[SPEAKER_33]: you know, fire hydrants or no parking at all, you know, this doesn't change any of that.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's only in the areas that currently have no restrictions on those streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: And it excludes paid to park areas, things like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: So this is filling in the gaps of public streets that are currently unrestricted that may become havens for people searching for parking that may want to use the Green Line or other reasons.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that's basically the outline of the proposal.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it won't change accessible parking spaces, anything like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: And the community does, regardless of what's approved tonight or not, the community would still have the opportunity to opt out by collecting petition for your particular street to get excluded from permanent parking and go back to unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_20]: Right.
[SPEAKER_20]: Director Blake, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioners, any comments or questions for Director Blake on this presentation?
[SPEAKER_16]: Yeah, I got one.
[SPEAKER_16]: Todd, you know, the list you generated before for the first 15, for this one in the agenda for the roads that say entire length, does that
[SPEAKER_16]: Does, does that mean that we already know that there's already no restrictions on the whole street so we're just moving forward with signing the whole thing?
[SPEAKER_33]: Very good question.
[SPEAKER_33]: That was meant to just describe the length of the street because some streets may already have a block or two restricted as permanent parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so it was meant to be.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's the entire street with the exceptions that I stated so.
[SPEAKER_33]: Okay, so yeah so so for instance North Street, their entire block say from Boston have cells that already have permit in their blocks from Boston up north that don't in some other will this is one where the middle third is already permit but the two ends are not permit.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so in those instances we highlighted block to block but for other streets we said the entire length, but there was a caveat Thank you for pointing that out to.
[SPEAKER_33]: It was a caveat at the bottom of the list that was posted that said some streets may even be partially private and partially public, and this is only meant to apply to the public portion of those streets.
[SPEAKER_16]: Got it.
[SPEAKER_16]: Okay, that answers my question.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Commissioner given any other commissioner comment question.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, I have a question.
[SPEAKER_30]: So when you're saying that it would be permit parking, but they could opt out, so then it would be permit parking on that particular street.
[SPEAKER_30]: It's not permit parking across the board.
[SPEAKER_30]: So if I live on Main Street and I want to park on Albion Street, I can or I can't.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's a good question.
[SPEAKER_33]: It seemed like two questions and one emery.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, you know what I'm trying to say it right but yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: For the first one.
[SPEAKER_33]: So this proposal is to make all public streets that don't already have permit parking which on this map the streets that are.
[SPEAKER_33]: colored in beige already have parking that streets that have blue don't have private parking and then pink or private ways.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we're trying to make all the blue beige as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: But yeah, the second part of your question I believe is, so the first part is, we want to do this.
[SPEAKER_33]: This proposal is meant to negate the need for all these 50 plus streets to have to go around getting a petition to become permit, because we see the need.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we're doing it all at once.
[SPEAKER_33]: But we're allowing the opposite to occur where if a street within this area show decided they did not want permit.
[SPEAKER_33]: Then they could collect signatures and submit that to traffic commission to take it away.
[SPEAKER_30]: Take it off.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, but but I think the second part of the question I think was about zone and district.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, current yeah that's a great point.
[SPEAKER_33]: Emery.
[SPEAKER_33]: This is currently still the street by street process so streets in this zone.
[SPEAKER_33]: In this area described on the map, and on the list would become permit but only for people on that street so North Street would be North Street West Street, but I mean, turns out it turns out, and there is a proposal recommended by the Commission on parking policy enforcement.
[SPEAKER_30]: to eventually go to a zona district where like one street could park on a neighboring street right it's over but that's not part of this current proposal okay yeah that may be some later yeah because i don't see how that's going to work if you know some streets are smaller than others there's two three family homes there's a lot of cars they're not going to fit so i don't know to me it seems like a lot of problems to try to keep everybody on their own street
[SPEAKER_33]: Yes, so one, one additional answer and then we'll go to other questions on.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's, it's a good concern and it's a good question, but I would go back to the original kind of point of permit parking is.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's not necessarily to guarantee everyone a space on this street, or in the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's just to limit the competition of others.
[SPEAKER_33]: So right now, these streets in these areas that don't have permit parking, anyone from elsewhere in Medford or other cities, Arlington, Belmont, or New York, could park there.
[SPEAKER_33]: So by going to permit, at least it limits the competition.
[SPEAKER_30]: But I think Todd, a lot of people are under the impression, I have permit parking, I'm guaranteed a space.
[SPEAKER_30]: And that's where the problem is, when it's a one, when it's street by street.
[SPEAKER_30]: And I think in Medford, that can't happen anymore.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, in none of our neighboring communities, none of them guarantee spaces.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_30]: That's where I think the problem started.
[SPEAKER_30]: It's, it's, it's impossible now to do street by street.
[SPEAKER_30]: So, but that was, that's what I was curious about.
[SPEAKER_30]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_33]: I think we have a couple other commissioners first, Alicia and Steve.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, uh, commissioner.
[SPEAKER_20]: Uh, commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_08]: You're muted, Steve.
[SPEAKER_21]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_21]: Are the terms and conditions and restrictions in this new area, Todd, the same as the ones that we voted on last time?
[SPEAKER_21]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_33]: HAB-Michael Leccesereeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeeee
[SPEAKER_21]: because we did have a lot of business people who came in on that last meeting and talked about how this could potentially be harmful.
[SPEAKER_21]: I just want to make sure this is something that this area as a whole is looking for, or as a majority is looking for, and not just, you know, five or six people who've got this in the agenda.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner Huff?
[SPEAKER_08]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry, I look like I'm looking at the map on my second screen.
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, I really, like you all know, I'm very much in favor of the regional permit parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, and when we looked at the inner region, um, I was very comfortable with it because the places where it seems like there are businesses and stuff that are going to be affected parks, they were going to have public parking next to them.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't have with this and maybe I'm missing it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Maybe I was sent it a street by street list with which ones are going to have
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, public parking paid a park or something and which are not because in this area, I'm looking at several public parks where residents park on the street to use those public parks.
[SPEAKER_08]: And suddenly those are going to permit parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I'm looking at South street that people park along.
[SPEAKER_08]: to access the Condon Shell and the farmer's market and things across the street there.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I know that there's a business on Winthrop Street where customers park particularly on West Street to access that business on Friday and Saturday and Sunday mornings.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I don't see any indication, I don't know from what I have in front of me that those are being addressed with this.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I really have concern with something that limits parking access for people to access our parks.
[SPEAKER_08]: Many of these parks are neighborhood parks, and that's lovely, but they should be able to drive over.
[SPEAKER_08]: And particularly the big one, Barrie, sometimes I get my parks wrong, park has ball fields and stuff.
[SPEAKER_08]: that people do need to drive over to.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I'm a little concerned about the details in this and not having access to the details.
[SPEAKER_33]: So the, the, it's a great point.
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you for that question.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, yeah, that wasn't necessarily explicitly listed in the exceptions but if we use the existing model that we have on other permit parking streets that existed before these two proposals.
[SPEAKER_33]: For instance on Morton Ave.
[SPEAKER_33]: The area of parking, alongside the park is on, even though Morton Ave is permit parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: the parking along the park is unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_33]: So as part of this proposal, parking alongside a park or a non-residential use, which that's what it is, would either be unrestricted or the two-hour variety.
[SPEAKER_33]: So there would be opportunity for other folks.
[SPEAKER_33]: If we model it after what currently exists in South Medford, the areas next to parks would remain unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_33]: But if those became a problem in a haven,
[SPEAKER_33]: the commission could consider like two hour, four hour, something like that to keep the eight hour, 10 hour people away that aren't from Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: So- I feel like I'd really want to, I'd like to double check the list and make sure that whoever's deciding which is which, that, I don't know, I just, I feel like we need to have some checks on that and make sure that it's correct.
[SPEAKER_33]: Well, so I could answer that along parks, it would be unrestricted if we, if we follow the model that Morton have already had in South Metro before these two proposals came about.
[SPEAKER_33]: So in the past the Traffic Commission approved current parking on Morton have the part that didn't that already had it between Medford and Winchester, but it excluded along the park, just like it typically excludes the businesses on the corners.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so it is meant to be in here it's just a extensive list to go through every detail of every.
[SPEAKER_33]: That's why we listen exceptions like going by uses residential uses the proposal says along residential uses and non residential uses.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so the intent is to keep the parks and other things like that available.
[SPEAKER_33]: And any of none of this precludes the commission from tweaking this further in the future, when individual issues like that arise from either businesses or parks and things like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: This is again just saving each individual street from coming, because those issues would exist with each individual street that came in of the 55 that came in requesting parent parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: That would be a question in that proposal.
[SPEAKER_33]: Anyways.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so this doesn't necessarily preclude us from the commission from looking into areas of it becomes problematic for businesses or things like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: In my gym, did you have anything to add to that.
[SPEAKER_09]: Sorry about that.
[SPEAKER_09]: Um, yes, I think I agree with Todd what Todd was was mentioning again along the parking on Morton Avenue we're looking at is sort of the same sort of process we would have at Barry Park for instance I believe you alluded to South Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: as well.
[SPEAKER_09]: And when we're looking at the area itself in this red zone here, District B, we're also taking into account the same sort of priorities we had with businesses.
[SPEAKER_09]: So if the business location, which you alluded to on West Street, I'm sure the majority of the parking is at the beginning of West.
[SPEAKER_09]: That would also be a two-hour parking to allow business activity.
[SPEAKER_09]: So each of those locations will be looked at and addressed accordingly.
[SPEAKER_08]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's really helpful.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for the question comments, Alicia, uh, commissioner hunt, uh, any other commissions before I open it up to public, any other comments, questions from the commissioners?
[SPEAKER_30]: Chief.
[SPEAKER_30]: I have a question for you.
[SPEAKER_30]: Um, cause I'm a little confused.
[SPEAKER_30]: There is another, um, group, another packing group that handles what's going on.
[SPEAKER_30]: with the green line and handling the streets and the problems they could have.
[SPEAKER_20]: It is this division.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_30]: Where does this fall under with the traffic commission versus them.
[SPEAKER_20]: The traffic regulatory body we're just creating in simple terms the rules of the city enforcement falls under the traffic division and with the Metro Police Department.
[SPEAKER_33]: Chief, if I may.
[SPEAKER_33]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_33]: In Marie I'm not sure if you mean the parking department or the, or the commission that I just referenced.
[SPEAKER_33]: So the mayor, about a year and a half ago.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, the mayor created a commission a temporary commission on parking policy and enforcement.
[SPEAKER_33]: that was made up of half residents, half of the group was residents, half were businesses, Jim Silva was on it.
[SPEAKER_33]: And then city employees attended that, including myself and the chief and city councilors.
[SPEAKER_33]: And it was a six month to a year process where that group of residents and business owners looked at parking issues throughout the entire city and came up with a list of recommendations.
[SPEAKER_33]: And they did surveys of residents and businesses
[SPEAKER_33]: They interviewed neighboring cities and towns what their policies were.
[SPEAKER_33]: So they weren't a regulatory body they were just convened to look at issues and how we can approach issues differently policy wise, and they came up with a list of recommendations in a report.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, that's what yeah that's what I wanted to know what they are.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, so they're, they're.
[SPEAKER_30]: Okay, so they just give a recommendations but it has to come to what they don't get a permit.
[SPEAKER_33]: Jim was on that and now is working a special price with the thing to add to my description of that group.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's, that's very, very true what you said Todd we had over 1000 responses from residents and over 100 businesses.
[SPEAKER_09]: we went through, we basically provided the city with a great deal of data, contemporary data, which we didn't have before.
[SPEAKER_09]: I, as co-chair, along with my other co-chair, are also the GLX representatives from the city of Medford.
[SPEAKER_09]: So we have been sort of working with community throughout the last six years, six and a half years, to work on
[SPEAKER_09]: looking at these particular problems that may occur.
[SPEAKER_09]: So this one was something that was important and was a constant conversation.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_30]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_30]: I get it.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think we should open this up to public comment.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mirella, you've been waiting for a while.
[SPEAKER_20]: You spoke up earlier.
[SPEAKER_03]: Also, I need to leave soon, and if I could talk after her.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I invite the public, if they could raise their hand, a little icon or something, we'll get them in there.
[SPEAKER_29]: Hi, can you hear me and see me?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, do you have comments related to the permit parking program?
[SPEAKER_29]: I have comments in reference to an application that I did for my parents for a handicap.
[SPEAKER_29]: spot in front of their house because they have serious mobility issues.
[SPEAKER_20]: OK, so that's going to be up next on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_20]: We have to get through this item first.
[SPEAKER_20]: I appreciate your patience, but I am obligated at this point to deal with one issue at a time.
[SPEAKER_20]: So if you could just hang on for a little while first.
[SPEAKER_29]: Let me ask you a question, because I'm in Boston.
[SPEAKER_29]: I'm at the JFK, and like I said, I need to get home.
[SPEAKER_29]: should I just take the phone with me and?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, I can, you know, I mean, is all the paperwork in on this?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, so I can tell you what, why don't you make your way home and try to log in when you get home.
[SPEAKER_20]: If you have no luck, reach out to the secretary of Erickson in the morning, and we'll give you the outcome of what happened this evening for you.
[SPEAKER_20]: We have your paperwork, we understand what the position is.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I think we're going to be on this issue for a little while.
[SPEAKER_20]: Hopefully you can get home.
[SPEAKER_20]: and then get logged back in, okay?
[SPEAKER_29]: Okay, I will try and log back in.
[SPEAKER_29]: I should be home by 6.15.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: We should be here.
[SPEAKER_29]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: All right, and I'm sorry if I pronounced this wrong.
[SPEAKER_03]: Alex is fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, thank you, you're welcome.
[SPEAKER_20]: And the floor is yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: Hi, I'm a resident on Walnut Street and South Street, who's concerned about the permit parking.
[SPEAKER_03]: In particular, the lack of zoning and having to do it by streets seems like it's a bit premature to do permit parking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like right now on my street, parking can get pretty full up and most of residents park on the neighboring streets.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that will basically mean that if we are limited to being permitted on our street, you're going to have a bunch of people who are just unable to park.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a huge issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: The other thing is I think residents around here occasionally have guests overnight.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it is very convenient, I think, for people to be able to have unrestricted parking.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think that by
[SPEAKER_03]: doing this for making it opt out rather than opt in makes it so that it doesn't really work in that it's very hard to collect petitions to opt out and if one street opts out but all the ones around them are all permitted then that street will have a congestion problem as opposed to right now like in this area there's no congestion problem we are
[SPEAKER_03]: about a mile away from the Green Line extension, and we don't have a congestion problem, and it's kind of unclear why we need to fix a problem that we don't have.
[SPEAKER_03]: So I'll try to keep it short and leave it at that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your comments, and thank you for your participation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Todd, you want to address that first, or I mean this?
[SPEAKER_33]: We can keep going, I think.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think in general, we're going to address that question again.
[SPEAKER_20]: But again, we're anticipating an increase in the amount of traffic of vehicles parking on our residential streets.
[SPEAKER_20]: And that's what we're trying to get ahead of with the opening of the Green Line extension later this fall.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I understand that there are more vehicles registered in Medford than we have parking spots.
[SPEAKER_20]: And it's a continuous battle no matter
[SPEAKER_20]: We're trying to stay ahead of it and deal with this but but I think we're going to get to all these questions and get answers as we move along, but at least we heard from you and took into consideration, and I'm just going to go across the board so I apologize if it's not perfectly in order.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hi there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, I live on Taylor street in Medford, which is just a couple blocks outside of that solid blue line.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, it's a very small street.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's just eight houses on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Two of which have an overcapacity of renters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Um, we also have, you know, our streets made smaller by.
[SPEAKER_01]: two of the driveways of the adjacent street fall on our street, which limits parking even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: We do have a significant congestion problem with parking on our street.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've been seeing an increase of vehicles from renters, from Airbnbs, which is a completely separate other problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also we've seen a significant uptick in commercial vehicles parking.
[SPEAKER_01]: um all of this ends up creating poor parking jobs which then creates obstruction to driveways hard to get in and out it's just overall been pretty problematic and a constant conversation amongst neighbors um so ultimately i would say we're
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm in favor of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I appreciate that it's being considered.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I just can't imagine it getting worse, which I anticipate it will with this because we are quite an easy walk to the green line or where it will be.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your comments and your participation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Much appreciated.
[SPEAKER_20]: Next up, P. Hanson.
[SPEAKER_26]: Hello, my name is Pat Hanson and my husband and I live on Toro Avenue.
[SPEAKER_26]: And we appreciate that this is being considered.
[SPEAKER_26]: At first I thought it was really bad, but then the more I understand the rationale, because it does make sense that our streets, we are within walking distance of the GLX.
[SPEAKER_26]: And my husband and I planted walk to the GLX.
[SPEAKER_26]: So we understand that it will be really congested on our streets from people from all over parking here.
[SPEAKER_26]: So we do understand why you wanna permit our area.
[SPEAKER_26]: The question was, we looked on the website and we couldn't figure out how much it would cost to get these permit parking stickers and what would we be allowed visitor passes as well.
[SPEAKER_29]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_29]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_33]: The proposed streets would have the same fees and structures for visitor passes and things like that, that all current parking streets.
[SPEAKER_08]: Todd, that information isn't on the city's website.
[SPEAKER_08]: I couldn't find it either.
[SPEAKER_08]: How much a resident permit costs and what are the policies for?
[SPEAKER_08]: If it's there, I can't find it.
[SPEAKER_09]: It should be on the parking page, Alicia.
[SPEAKER_09]: I believe it's on the parking page itself, price listing.
[SPEAKER_09]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_20]: And it should be $10 plus two, it comes with two visitor passes.
[SPEAKER_26]: Okay, beautiful, thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your comments and questions and your participation, much appreciated.
[SPEAKER_18]: The only other thing would be for, like they're saying about individual street parking and not having to be in regional for certain areas.
[SPEAKER_18]: There are a lot of triple deckers here and they park everywhere.
[SPEAKER_18]: This is Bill Hanson.
[SPEAKER_18]: Uh, so is there anything in consideration going to happen with that?
[SPEAKER_18]: Or is that going to be down the road a while?
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_33]: Um, that's a great question.
[SPEAKER_33]: A great comment.
[SPEAKER_33]: Um, so.
[SPEAKER_33]: As alluded to this, this is a step we're taking.
[SPEAKER_33]: It doesn't at this time include zone or district.
[SPEAKER_33]: That is a larger conversation to be had, but I think some of you are helping that conversation in the sense that you're recognizing that zone or district may be more beneficial.
[SPEAKER_33]: in the same type of conversation with the community will be had when that topic comes up.
[SPEAKER_33]: There are some people that don't necessarily agree with that approach.
[SPEAKER_32]: Excuse me.
[SPEAKER_33]: So comments like yourself, and once you have permanent parking, people may realize that that's more beneficial to go to its own district situation.
[SPEAKER_33]: This doesn't preclude that future.
[SPEAKER_26]: Okay, great.
[SPEAKER_26]: The other thing we're concerned about is our area, a lot of houses are for sale.
[SPEAKER_26]: And from where there was just one single family, now all of a sudden there's two, there's an area around South Street that's gonna become four houses.
[SPEAKER_26]: So that's heading to the congestion of the whole area, parking-wise.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so that gets back to my point early on when presenting.
[SPEAKER_33]: Green Line is one major impetus to do this, but there are other reasons that marketing is congested, right?
[SPEAKER_26]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_26]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your participation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Beth Fuller, I believe, from my eyes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Hi, how are you?
[SPEAKER_36]: Hi, Beth Fuller, 15 West Street.
[SPEAKER_36]: Thank you, Alicia, for bringing up the Goldilocks.
[SPEAKER_36]: business.
[SPEAKER_36]: Goldilocks has been a wonderful neighbor, much better than Stone and Skillet ever was.
[SPEAKER_36]: However,
[SPEAKER_36]: their employees don't just park right at the Goldilocks itself, but do park a little bit further away.
[SPEAKER_36]: I want to ensure that they're taken care of in some way so that we're not making it so much more difficult for the people who work at Goldilocks to find parking.
[SPEAKER_36]: And then the second issue is that the ball fields, I think they're Memorial ball fields, which is on Winthrop Street,
[SPEAKER_36]: They tend to park for ball games, Little League games.
[SPEAKER_36]: They tend to park on West Street on Saturdays.
[SPEAKER_36]: And there really is no other place for them to go to.
[SPEAKER_36]: If you go to the parking lot behind the bandshell, then you're going to have traffic backing up on Winthrop Street as traffic has stopped to allow families to cross.
[SPEAKER_36]: Just want to make sure that those things will be addressed in some way so that we're not, as Alicia said, not inhibiting access to the ball fields by other teams that are coming in and for the players and families themselves.
[SPEAKER_36]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_36]: And also the traffic for Goldilocks actually goes almost to the end of West Street.
[SPEAKER_36]: It goes almost to Lyman Street.
[SPEAKER_36]: It is a very popular place.
[SPEAKER_36]: on Fridays, Saturdays, and Sundays.
[SPEAKER_20]: Understood that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your participation and your comments.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Elise.
[SPEAKER_27]: Hello, everyone.
[SPEAKER_27]: First of all, I want to commend the city of Medford for being proactive about this.
[SPEAKER_27]: And I have what I hope is a quick question.
[SPEAKER_27]: I'm not used to permit parking.
[SPEAKER_27]: My house address is actually on Winthrop Street, but I'm right on the corner of Summer.
[SPEAKER_27]: So I would be parking on Summer.
[SPEAKER_27]: So if permit parking is going to be by street, then what do I do?
[SPEAKER_27]: Where can I park?
[SPEAKER_33]: Usually in that case, someone that's on a corner lot could, if both streets have permit, which in this process they would, I believe, correct me if I'm wrong, Chief, they could choose which street.
[SPEAKER_33]: And in this case, you'd obviously choose Summer Street.
[SPEAKER_27]: Well, I'd have to choose Summer because there's no parking on Winthrop.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, Chief, do you concur with
[SPEAKER_33]: It echoes the existing policy.
[SPEAKER_33]: If you're on a street with permit on a corner in a street by street, that corner house could choose which one.
[SPEAKER_33]: So summer street would apply to this person.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, that's correct.
[SPEAKER_20]: Nothing has changed as it relates to corner houses.
[SPEAKER_20]: You would be summer street, no issues.
[SPEAKER_27]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_27]: Thank you so much for answering that question.
[SPEAKER_27]: Um, I also like commissioner hunt couldn't find information on the website.
[SPEAKER_27]: Otherwise I would have spared you the time.
[SPEAKER_27]: So thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your comment.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Uh, Jessica, please.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hi everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: My name is Jessica Messina.
[SPEAKER_00]: I live on winter street.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, and my question is surrounding the 24 six regulation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Um, and apologies if this was brought up in a previous meeting,
[SPEAKER_00]: If so, you can skip right over me.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I know it's been said a couple of times tonight that the GLX was only one of the quote unquote major impetuses for doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So just kind of wanted to know the rational behind it being the 24-6 rather than something that avoids the kind of like the commuter parking, maybe like eight to six permit only.
[SPEAKER_00]: As someone else mentioned, you know, having guests over more than two cars would be a challenge for that 24-6.
[SPEAKER_00]: would love to get some information behind that.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, thank you for your question.
[SPEAKER_33]: So there have been issues just in terms of congestion and growth.
[SPEAKER_33]: multi family uses things like that more car ownership.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, for instance, in South Medford and hillside in the original district and then this larger district, more than half the public streets say say about 60% already had per parking long before the Green Line has come about right so so they asked for parking for a reason because they were experiencing issues.
[SPEAKER_33]: And usually, those issues just grow and expand to the adjacent streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: So this is kind of getting in front of it in terms of in terms of the visitors, you know, there is a program to have visitor parking passes for each.
[SPEAKER_33]: resident.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, it just echoes that same system we're not changing anything that would have existed, if each of your streets went with a petition to get permanent parking individually, we're just doing it much faster.
[SPEAKER_33]: So none of those programs related to visitor or non visitor changes in terms of that process in terms of the time of day.
[SPEAKER_33]: One thing that was highlighted in the Commission on Park Policy and Enforcement's report is the
[SPEAKER_33]: varying degree of existing restrictions all across the city in this, in this neighborhood and South Medford and hillside as well, where some streets have these are some streets have these are some streets have these are so we're trying to be one message in that report is very clear to be more consistency, and it also lends itself to be more consistent enforcement as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: So the 24-6 seems like a balance between 24-7 and other elements of day versus night.
[SPEAKER_33]: If we only do day, it addresses commuters, but not necessarily other issues going on.
[SPEAKER_33]: And if we only do night, the opposite.
[SPEAKER_33]: There was a lot of consideration for a number of different options, but that's the option we've landed on to be most consistent with most of the existing restricted streets.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that totally answers my question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thanks.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your comments, question, and participation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Eunice, you're up next.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, thanks very much.
[SPEAKER_04]: Good evening.
[SPEAKER_04]: Eunice Brown Greenleaf Avenue.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm definitely in support of extending the permit reach, as, as you've indicated, but hand in hand with that, and I don't know if it's
[SPEAKER_04]: you guys or the parking department or in tandem, we really need the window stickers back.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'll address the problems on Greenleaf later when my neighbor brings up Greenleaf later on.
[SPEAKER_04]: She's got an agenda item, but there's right now no way for us to tell if a car belongs on the street or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we certainly,
[SPEAKER_04]: The fine men and women of the Medford Police Department have their hands full with so many other things that we don't want to be calling you to come out all the time, you know, to determine whether or not a vehicle belongs there.
[SPEAKER_04]: And we really have no idea, at least I don't.
[SPEAKER_04]: how frequently the parking department comes around and monitors and then, you know, checks the plates and so forth to determine whether or not a car belongs there.
[SPEAKER_04]: So I think if you're going to do this and extend the reach, then you need to bring back the window stickers.
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, they were a godsend.
[SPEAKER_04]: And without those, you know, and with a
[SPEAKER_04]: parking department that's probably understaffed as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: I just don't see how this works effectively without the ability for residents to report things going on in their neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_04]: So those stickers really need to come back.
[SPEAKER_04]: I don't know why they went away.
[SPEAKER_04]: I understand the need to go paperless, but I don't understand why they went away in the first place.
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you very much for that comment.
[SPEAKER_33]: I would say we're not necessarily picking up the sticker and no sticker issue tonight, but there are a number of us on this call, including myself and others who could report back to the parking department and the administration with that comment.
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Welcome.
[SPEAKER_20]: Much appreciated.
[SPEAKER_20]: It is being debated.
[SPEAKER_20]: So thank you for your comment.
[SPEAKER_20]: Pat Barry, please.
[SPEAKER_34]: Hi, my name is Pat Barry.
[SPEAKER_34]: I am a resident, lifelong resident of Taylor Street, and I want to applaud Eunice for what she just said.
[SPEAKER_34]: I also want to applaud my co-resident Chrissy who spoke earlier about Taylor Street and our parking difficulties.
[SPEAKER_34]: Yes, I'm in agreement there should be stickers.
[SPEAKER_34]: We have
[SPEAKER_34]: are too many people that are coming and parking on a very small street that's overcrowded to begin with, and no way of identifying them as they become transient, like, especially with the identification of potentially having Airbnbs being set up without our knowing it.
[SPEAKER_34]: The other thing that I'd like to ask in regards to, and by the way, I agree with the permit parking situation, absolutely applaud the situation, and I applaud the city of Medford for being as proactive about addressing this and wanting to enforce it in the way that they're approaching it.
[SPEAKER_34]: I'd like to also ask, we have an adjoining street, Martin Street, which is a one-sided parking only street.
[SPEAKER_34]: How are streets such as that to be affected?
[SPEAKER_34]: I'm not certain as to why the full extent of Martin Street was selected as being a one-sided only parking street.
[SPEAKER_34]: I know in part, and I've been here with my own family emergencies and stuff, that it makes it difficult in certain aspects of the street for emergency vehicles to make the corners and the swings.
[SPEAKER_34]: However, the adjoining street, Marshall Street, doesn't have one-sided.
[SPEAKER_34]: And what happens is, with Martin being a dead end, we have an over-influx of cars parking on Taylor Street, which, we're a short street, we don't have enough parking for anyways.
[SPEAKER_34]: But in addition, we have seen a significant increase in commercial vehicles parking overnight.
[SPEAKER_34]: I have a truck vehicle parked in front of my own house currently that is a commercial vehicle.
[SPEAKER_34]: And I know the police have been lately ticketing this person for parking on Mason Street.
[SPEAKER_34]: and yet he's back to parking on Taylor Street when he's a resident of Martin Street.
[SPEAKER_34]: How do we deal with that?
[SPEAKER_34]: How do we deal with not being able to identify vehicles and being residents?
[SPEAKER_34]: And what suggestions do you have for us to respond to those circumstances?
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you for your questions and comments in regard to a sweeping one side versus two sided.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's usually depending on the width of the street.
[SPEAKER_33]: And I wouldn't make any promises here but we could revisit that street or another street to remeasure to see if we could maybe accommodate or not.
[SPEAKER_33]: In terms of that other.
[SPEAKER_33]: a car from a different street park on your street, I guess what if this gets approved, that would be solved because it would only be limited to Taylor Street.
[SPEAKER_33]: And then if it went to zone districts, I guess it would resurface itself again.
[SPEAKER_33]: But the business component of it is something separate as well, which the city with a lot of
[SPEAKER_33]: The changing economy and things not being as clear with business vehicles, as they once were in terms of writing on the versus, you know,
[SPEAKER_33]: person owned businesses and things like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: Those are policies that are also being looked into and the commission on parking policy and enforcement made some recommendations regarding that as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so that could be changing at some point, but, um, but these are things we're willing to work with community on and, um, press forward and, you know, take these incremental steps to improve, but not necessarily.
[SPEAKER_33]: Come up with a perfect situation right now, but constantly improve and doesn't preclude improving at a later date.
[SPEAKER_34]: Excuse me, Todd, but isn't there an ordinance in place already in regards to commercial vehicle parking overnight that prevents it?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yes, I believe so.
[SPEAKER_33]: Again, the commission has looked into this and with the change in economy and a lot more people owning their own businesses and not necessarily have a business address and things like that, there may be exceptions or permits in the future.
[SPEAKER_33]: But yeah, as currently written, I believe you're correct.
[SPEAKER_34]: Okay, because what happens is they park their commercial vehicles here, their workers come to get the commercial vehicle, park their vehicles on the street, and then it's a constant battle for getting parking spaces available, because the workers are coming to pick up the commercial vehicle, leaving their cars, our residents come to come home,
[SPEAKER_34]: can't get a parking spot because these places being taken up by these people that work for these quote companies, and yet, then they pull off in the commercial vehicles allowed to park there.
[SPEAKER_34]: It's very frustrating.
[SPEAKER_33]: We appreciate the comment I guess in the short term.
[SPEAKER_33]: If I'm understanding you correctly, the personal vehicles for the workers would not no longer be allowed because of the permit in your area.
[SPEAKER_33]: So then that may negate them from doing that potentially.
[SPEAKER_34]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_34]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I'll lastly, I'll just add that this is one of the reasons why I have my traffic supervisors here.
[SPEAKER_20]: They run the traffic unit and they can, they hear these problems every month and they can sort of address them.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I know Sergeant Rogers was just talking about that specific example, so we can get some enforcement down in that area.
[SPEAKER_34]: Yeah, Leo's plastering, you know the vehicle.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for your participation and comments.
[SPEAKER_20]: Next up, Amnagem.
[SPEAKER_23]: I welcome my name is Anita Nagel.
[SPEAKER_23]: I live on Norton Avenue, just off of north street.
[SPEAKER_23]: And from the perspective of people who live in my area, the scope of this proposal is excessive.
[SPEAKER_23]: It looks like it was developed by someone who has no understanding of the neighborhood, our neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_23]: Norton Avenue is an extremely small street.
[SPEAKER_23]: It's a private way, one block long.
[SPEAKER_23]: There is barely enough parking on this street for the residents.
[SPEAKER_23]: There are a few spots on the street where people can park without blocking other residents.
[SPEAKER_23]: If we have any visitors, if we have any renovations done, we need to park on North street or have our visitors park on North street.
[SPEAKER_23]: Walkling Court is just on the other side of North Street.
[SPEAKER_23]: There are quite a few residents of Walkling Court who park on North Street or Auburn or in the neighborhood because there is extremely limited parking there.
[SPEAKER_23]: Limiting this to permit parking only is going to significantly
[SPEAKER_23]: affect the lives of quite a few people in this area.
[SPEAKER_23]: I know some people in Walkland Court would not be able to live there anymore if they were not able to park their car on a city street.
[SPEAKER_23]: There is no parking or extremely limited parking in Walkland Court.
[SPEAKER_23]: If they don't have access to their car, they would have to find another place to live.
[SPEAKER_23]: So limiting parking on Auburn North street, the area would be a significant hindrance
[SPEAKER_23]: to their ability to live independently.
[SPEAKER_23]: And this seems, at least for our area to be a solution in search of a problem.
[SPEAKER_23]: If something comes up, we could certainly address the issue and opt into this, but
[SPEAKER_23]: Having this be a blanket declaration of permit parking only is going to have a lot of negative impacts in this area.
[SPEAKER_23]: I have spoken with about 15 neighbors of mine on Norton Ave and on North street, and everyone is universally opposed to this.
[SPEAKER_20]: Well, thank you for your comments.
[SPEAKER_20]: Todd, you want to address it first?
[SPEAKER_33]: I'm sorry I was trying to get the link to the Commission on partner policy enforcement.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, no, the point is well taken.
[SPEAKER_33]: Streets in the areas that seem to be on the peripheral of the zone like that particular neighborhood that's probably the furthest from the new Greenland stations.
[SPEAKER_33]: They will have the option to opt out so I spoke to someone on North Street in that block earlier today.
[SPEAKER_33]: And that is an option.
[SPEAKER_33]: And I, you know, we understand that that's could be time soon to get signatures but, you know,
[SPEAKER_33]: weighing that against all the people wanted this time soon for them to get signatures so again this is this was looked at holistically so choosing the majority and trying to do this proactively quicker but still allowing folks that may not want it the ability to come back with petition to not have it seemed like a
[SPEAKER_33]: a balance that we could live with in terms of weighing all these things in terms of Norton.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, for that private way we, the chief and I did hold a private informational meeting regarding private
[SPEAKER_33]: parking on private ways, and we can provide the link in the chat for that as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: So there are some things available to someone like folks on Norton other private ways that you can control your own parking potentially per mass general law.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, in terms of other areas that would be available for someone in your neighborhood that didn't have a permit.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, based on the comment by.
[SPEAKER_33]: Alicia Hunt earlier and then based on our responses to that, Cummings Park adjacent to Cummings Park would be unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_33]: Some spot on West Street adjacent to Mystic River would be unrestricted and some spot on Auburn Street adjacent to Mystic River would also be unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_33]: So between those four areas, that's four areas of about
[SPEAKER_33]: 30 feet, 130 feet, 160 feet, and 190 feet that would remain unrestricted in those areas.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it's just an area that would allow some relief for people that did not have permits in that area to utilize those amenities, but as well as issues that you mentioned.
[SPEAKER_23]: Well, when I contacted you and I asked you about a variance, you said that we could petition the city and we may be able to get a variance if we did not live adjacent to one of these streets.
[SPEAKER_33]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so, so if you're one of the four houses on the corner of Norton so the two hours on the corner Norton and North, you could likely get a permit on North, and if you're one of the two on the corner alignment you likely could get a permanent line.
[SPEAKER_33]: There's nothing restricting you from requesting a variance.
[SPEAKER_33]: for folks that aren't on the corner, but based on my history with the commission, the corner houses typically will get those whereas the others.
[SPEAKER_33]: you know, may or may not.
[SPEAKER_33]: So I couldn't answer if the commission would approve variances like that, but that may be another avenue.
[SPEAKER_33]: But again, I'm gonna include in the chat a link to the information that the chief and I gave for folks that live on private ways that- Yes, I already have that.
[SPEAKER_33]: If private ways, in some instances, it gives you more control than folks living on a public way.
[SPEAKER_23]: The control of the street is really not the issue of this.
[SPEAKER_23]: The problem is that the street is so small, again, with anyone comes to visit, right now, I have some neighbors who had to have a dumpster put on the street.
[SPEAKER_23]: That blocks off a parking spot, it means people who live here cannot park where they usually do.
[SPEAKER_23]: I mean, this is going to be an issue every time anyone has anything done on their house.
[SPEAKER_23]: And again, whenever you have a visitor.
[SPEAKER_23]: I mean, these places are not adjacent to the street.
[SPEAKER_23]: It's gonna be a bit complicated to tell people, oh, go around the corner.
[SPEAKER_23]: And because these are one-way streets, have them drive all the way around to find a spot where they can park.
[SPEAKER_23]: Again, in this area, it is a solution in search of a problem.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you for your comments and for participating this evening.
[SPEAKER_20]: Are there any other public,
[SPEAKER_20]: comments or questions.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, seeing none, I'll close this portion of the public comments and go back to our commissioners based on what you've heard.
[SPEAKER_20]: Any question, comments, thoughts, motions?
[SPEAKER_20]: That's to my commissioners.
[SPEAKER_16]: Yeah, this is Tim.
[SPEAKER_16]: but I think there was someone else wanted to go too, but my thought is that it was intriguing to hear the comment about a solution in search of a problem, because I will say that we don't necessarily know that this is gonna be a problem, right, in these areas.
[SPEAKER_16]: The quarter mile list, which was the 15 streets, and we were basically filling in the gaps, that one, my level of comfort was high.
[SPEAKER_16]: This one isn't just because of some of the issues that have been brought up.
[SPEAKER_16]: Um, and because it's street by street, when we do zones, some of the issues will be resolved.
[SPEAKER_16]: Like, you know, um, you know, you can only talk on this street, not the other street, for example, that will be eliminated with zone.
[SPEAKER_16]: So I'm just wondering, you know, if, uh, if that's a salient point in other commissioners heads as well.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, I'm, I'm not convinced.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I did, I feel like when we heard from the residents who are saying, but why aren't we included?
[SPEAKER_08]: Those were the ones that were a blockers about a block outside of the blue, the blue section, the section we approved last time.
[SPEAKER_08]: And
[SPEAKER_08]: the people that we're hearing from who are very opposed, and that's really the quarter mile circle.
[SPEAKER_08]: When we hear from the people within, we heard from the people within a quarter, sorry, half mile.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm looking at the, be easier, I got a copy on my desk.
[SPEAKER_08]: the half mile circle, those people were kind of like, ugh, us too, we're gonna have trouble.
[SPEAKER_08]: The people who have named what streets they're on were saying, why are we doing this?
[SPEAKER_08]: They're outside the half mile circle and they have no reason, they don't believe they're gonna see these problems.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I don't know, I'm not sure they will.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm not, I guess I'm sort of, I kind of feel like I want to sleep on this some more.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm not feeling ready to approve it blanketly tonight.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't mean that that means we shouldn't ever.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm wondering if we can.
[SPEAKER_33]: I just wanted to point something out.
[SPEAKER_33]: So Toro Avenue, we've heard from folks there and Taylor, they're both outside the half mile.
[SPEAKER_33]: and they were in favor and they're equally distant from the person on Walnut who was against which they're all about 3000 feet from the top station.
[SPEAKER_33]: So I guess the commission has a right to feel the way they do.
[SPEAKER_33]: I guess I would, the half mile, if it were a half mile, the border would roughly be Willis, Summer and say Adams, right?
[SPEAKER_33]: So Willis to the Northeast, Summer to the North and Adams.
[SPEAKER_33]: The amount of remaining streets at that point would be limited, and it would exclude streets like Toro and Taylor, which you said they wanted.
[SPEAKER_08]: You know what, Todd, I have a problem here.
[SPEAKER_08]: You heard, somebody heard.
[SPEAKER_08]: I haven't seen one email, one message.
[SPEAKER_08]: I heard the people at the hearing last time.
[SPEAKER_08]: But those comments have not been conveyed to us.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we're not, we're not feeling it is part of the problem.
[SPEAKER_08]: We're not included in this, like feedback that the city is getting.
[SPEAKER_08]: I am the city, but I'm not the part that heard from anybody.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I guess part of the difficulty here, right?
[SPEAKER_08]: Like you're hearing but I didn't get a list of here all the people who sent comments or
[SPEAKER_33]: inundate me with 500 pages of email so that I can see it to the streets that I just mentioned were streets mentioned tonight that we all heard.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, so I guess I'm just pointing out and also I refer back to the Commission on Parking Policy and Enforcement, which did do an extensive number of outreach and looked into all these issues and this is building off of that report.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it's, it's not an isolated
[SPEAKER_16]: So, what about the concern though, we're doing the street by street, so we've got this bigger area now and we're doing a street by street, where, you know, there's issues that we already identified we talked about the first 15 and a quarter mile area, because we're doing a street by street and otherwise it's not zoned yet.
[SPEAKER_16]: So what we're saying, street by street parking in this whole area, so you have to park on your street and you can't go to another street.
[SPEAKER_16]: So without having the full zone parking, like if this was zone Q or whatever, those issues wouldn't exist.
[SPEAKER_16]: And that's tied directly to, are we solving a problem that doesn't exist at the moment?
[SPEAKER_16]: We know that those first 15 streets in that quarter mile, a lot of those streets that were blue,
[SPEAKER_16]: were sort of anomalous.
[SPEAKER_16]: They were non-restricted parking with lots of restricted parking around it.
[SPEAKER_16]: And now if you zoom out,
[SPEAKER_16]: We're talking about sections of the city.
[SPEAKER_16]: There's a whole section that doesn't have any permanent parking right now.
[SPEAKER_16]: It's completely unrestricted.
[SPEAKER_16]: So I think the context is different between what we saw for the first 15 and now what we're looking at today.
[SPEAKER_16]: In my mind, it's kind of touching upon that.
[SPEAKER_16]: Are we trying to solve a problem that doesn't exist yet?
[SPEAKER_16]: And are we jumping the gun here?
[SPEAKER_16]: So anyway, I just want to proceed with caution.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm with Alicia.
[SPEAKER_16]: I don't think we're saying no, we don't want to do this.
[SPEAKER_16]: I think we're saying, oh, are we ready to do this?
[SPEAKER_16]: Right today.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, yes, those are all those are all great points I guess I would say, if we tallied up the amount of people on tonight's meeting, the number of streets that said they didn't want it.
[SPEAKER_33]: How many are we talking about I think it's only a couple to a few.
[SPEAKER_08]: In my opinion, I mean it's not really about voting now.
[SPEAKER_20]: I agree with most of the points.
[SPEAKER_21]: I think there's got to come a point where we just draw a fine line where we stop the opt in and then, you know, or stop the opt out and start the opt in.
[SPEAKER_21]: Like, you know, I mean, I mean, we're already at Goldilocks.
[SPEAKER_21]: So the concerns that they have, and I'll be honest, I don't even see that being remotely close to where this T station is going to be.
[SPEAKER_21]: So eventually.
[SPEAKER_21]: I'd like to stop at where we are and then see what happens and then go from there.
[SPEAKER_21]: I mean, adding another agenda item to a street that has issues with the parking.
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't see that as being a problem.
[SPEAKER_21]: Last week I thought, or last time we met, I thought it was very amicable and very supportive.
[SPEAKER_21]: This week I kind of get the tone like we're cramming stuff down their throats.
[SPEAKER_21]: And so if there are people out there who have concerns about this,
[SPEAKER_21]: And I understand the parking commission put a lot of work into their plan.
[SPEAKER_21]: It sounds like they didn't get to everybody.
[SPEAKER_21]: And I'd like this issue to continue to be looked at as we start to expand the circle a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_21]: And so that's the only concern I have.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right.
[SPEAKER_08]: I feel like we're also, there are people who, I mean, honestly, the parking report recommends zone parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that I feel like I heard from people tonight who if what it meant was you can park on any of the streets in your neighborhood, your surrounding streets, you just need a permit, and other people from other parts of the city can't, they might have actually not been as opposed to it.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I have heard that we're not ready for zone parking yet.
[SPEAKER_08]: I invite the city, somebody to propose the zone parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I realized that we just permitted all the street by streets.
[SPEAKER_08]: Like the difficulty is, I'm not sure we should make the people feel like this pain of like having to stay on your one street to be able to love zone parking, permit parking.
[SPEAKER_20]: Can I get a comment from you?
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah, well, that that was my point, I think, as Alicia said, you know, it's like, how do you keep people just on their street?
[SPEAKER_30]: And I think that's, you know, if you have permit parking, then you can park on any street within the permits up there.
[SPEAKER_30]: But I like what Steve said to, you know, opt in rather than opt out.
[SPEAKER_30]: I think it's too much too soon.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, and just keep in mind the fact that 60%, I believe, Director Boyd said, are already street-by-street resident permit parking.
[SPEAKER_20]: So those are restricted to those streets.
[SPEAKER_08]: Can we see that map again that he shared?
[SPEAKER_08]: Last time I had the opportunity to have that map in advance that shows what's already permit parking and what isn't.
[SPEAKER_08]: And so I don't have a copy of this on my desk now.
[SPEAKER_20]: You can see it.
[SPEAKER_08]: There is a lot.
[SPEAKER_08]: All the yellow ones already have permit parking, and it's the blue ones that are under consideration here.
[SPEAKER_16]: In the area I was talking about, Alicia, that doesn't have any currently, you can see it up in the upper left corner.
[SPEAKER_16]: Right.
[SPEAKER_09]: And I also add this is the first time that we're having main streets to be included in a parking program so a lot of the blue is the largest streets such as main street Boston Avenue.
[SPEAKER_09]: etc.
[SPEAKER_09]: Winchester Street Medford Street.
[SPEAKER_09]: So, you'll see that there's a great deal of blue, because the extensive amount of those main streets that before people who lived on those streets did not have the possibility of resident parking.
[SPEAKER_16]: I feel like we're seeing the start of a really good zone.
[SPEAKER_16]: This, maybe this is one or two zones.
[SPEAKER_20]: But the risk of turning this into a debate over zone parking, we have an agenda item that is not zone parking, which we have to address.
[SPEAKER_20]: And so, I mean, the commissioners have, they know their options.
[SPEAKER_20]: They can motion to approve, motion to disapprove, table the item, you know, leave it in your hands where your thoughts are.
[SPEAKER_08]: Chief, we have two residents with their hands raised and I realize we're past that, but one of them I believe was the co-chair of the parking committee that we've been referencing.
[SPEAKER_20]: Hi everyone.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, yeah, floor's yours.
[SPEAKER_38]: Laurel Roma 149 Burgett Avenue and Jim Silva and I were co-chairs of the parking enforcement commission.
[SPEAKER_38]: So I just want to make it clear that the MBTA themselves have declared one mile radius is the willingness of people to park and walk to the train station.
[SPEAKER_38]: So our idea was not to inflict more pain onto folks because we know it's already difficult parking in our neighborhoods because we also live here.
[SPEAKER_38]: But also just to make the point that people are going to park on North Street and walk anyway.
[SPEAKER_38]: And I hate to say it, but maybe we just need to kind of wait and see what happens come November.
[SPEAKER_38]: And November is technically when the last time the MBTA said,
[SPEAKER_38]: that the green line would start running.
[SPEAKER_38]: So perhaps it's the wait and see measure, but on the table right now, just to let you know that area in red that is scheduled to go all permit parking, those signs won't be installed until October 15th.
[SPEAKER_38]: And that was voted on last month.
[SPEAKER_38]: So if we wait until November and the GLX starts and the streets are flooded and we have to wait another X amount of months
[SPEAKER_38]: to get the signs in, to order the signs, get the signs installed, you could be looking at it as more serious delay than now.
[SPEAKER_38]: Just something to think of.
[SPEAKER_38]: Every street has to kind of consider their own circumstances.
[SPEAKER_38]: But thank you all very much for your participation.
[SPEAKER_38]: It's greatly appreciated.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you, Laura.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thanks for your comments.
[SPEAKER_16]: Chief, I can speak to a couple of Laura's points.
[SPEAKER_16]: We're planning on
[SPEAKER_16]: you know, purchasing signs and poles for the entire, you know, basically this list, the list before, because what we're trying to do is make it so when zone comes about, we can just put little zone placards on.
[SPEAKER_16]: So we're buying two types of signs, we're buying lots of them, hundreds and hundreds of them to gear up for the first 15, and then these ones, and then the rest of the city as it comes.
[SPEAKER_16]: So we're dealing with those backlogs and preparing now.
[SPEAKER_16]: So I don't think whether we vote on this tonight or we vote on this at some point in the future, when we have a little bit more information, it's going to impact the rollout of all this.
[SPEAKER_16]: We're already sort of up against the deadline, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_16]: So, and we're doing everything we can to get all, there's like, there's backlogs on polls, there's issues with signs.
[SPEAKER_16]: So we're trying to get, you know, work through all these issues now before this happens.
[SPEAKER_16]: So just to kind of touch upon that.
[SPEAKER_16]: give you some confidence.
[SPEAKER_20]: Let me throw this out to the commissioners as a thought process.
[SPEAKER_20]: Should they vote this down or table it?
[SPEAKER_20]: What's your thoughts when or if any street wants to opt in next month separately and independently?
[SPEAKER_20]: Would they entertain that or would they want to wait for a decision on this?
[SPEAKER_20]: In other words,
[SPEAKER_20]: There is still an opt-in.
[SPEAKER_20]: Someone in, let's say for example, Street in North Medford could come next month and opt-in to a resident firm in Black and Brown.
[SPEAKER_20]: Any of these streets?
[SPEAKER_08]: I guess I would be very open to that.
[SPEAKER_08]: If North Street came in next month and said, we collected the signatures, we want in and we want in now and we're not waiting.
[SPEAKER_08]: then I would respect that because they brought the signatures and I believe we've asked for at least 50%.
[SPEAKER_08]: Usually when we've gotten these, they've had very significant percentage to the point where I don't ask what the low number is because it's always more like 80% of the people have signed on to it when it's come in front of us.
[SPEAKER_21]: I agree with that.
[SPEAKER_21]: I won't support tabling this.
[SPEAKER_21]: I think at this point, I will support more of an opt-in position.
[SPEAKER_21]: And I agree with Alicia.
[SPEAKER_21]: If a street comes in and says, we're ready to go, here we go, I like that Tim is ordering extra supplies so that if we do start to see the influx like the parking commission is envisioning,
[SPEAKER_21]: that it won't be that much of a delay, at least to get to those first few streets.
[SPEAKER_21]: I still think this is gonna be like a concentric type building where it's gonna be the next street, the next street, the next street, see where it stops.
[SPEAKER_21]: But I really ask this commission not to table this, because I think at this point, we need to start going more toward an opt-in type position.
[SPEAKER_20]: And so that's the reason I asked that question, because I think the options before us, Commissioner Kaczynski,
[SPEAKER_20]: someone like yourself, based on what you just said, um, to, um, put a motion on the floor to deny this, uh, petition, um, with the understanding that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Uh, business as usual, and you could opt in as opposed to tabling it or approval, but that's not the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_20]: And I just feel a little bit so that, um, we can move one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_20]: The commission sounds to me like they're.
[SPEAKER_16]: of like mind.
[SPEAKER_16]: So a procedural question, Chief, if we were to deny this tonight, is there a time restriction or a waiting period that has to happen before it can be brought onto the agenda again?
[SPEAKER_20]: Six months, yes, six months.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's why I would like to table it because here's my scenario.
[SPEAKER_08]: We table it.
[SPEAKER_08]: They open up the green line the first week of November.
[SPEAKER_08]: The third week in November, people are screaming bloody murder.
[SPEAKER_08]: Oh my God, the parking is out of control, like the whole area.
[SPEAKER_08]: We hold a special meeting, we reconsider it and we pass it immediately.
[SPEAKER_21]: That could happen.
[SPEAKER_21]: But technically, if the next item is a street by street, it's not the same as a global.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right, that would be different.
[SPEAKER_21]: So what I'm saying is- So if we vote this down, it seems like if we vote this global thing down, the next one won't be a global.
[SPEAKER_21]: It will be North Street or whatever street.
[SPEAKER_21]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_08]: And that's not the same early.
[SPEAKER_08]: Some of these streets will probably show up, but it's a lot of work to get those signatures.
[SPEAKER_08]: And some of those streets will show up next month and ask us to pass it.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then we'll pass a handful.
[SPEAKER_08]: And then the traffic, the parking will become out of control in late November.
[SPEAKER_08]: and the city will be under pressure to do this, to bring this same proposal back.
[SPEAKER_08]: But all the people who spoke against it, if 20 people spoke against it tonight, I would think we would have two against it then, because all the people who spoke tonight would show up saying, we didn't realize this would happen.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah, respectfully, I will not support tabling it.
[SPEAKER_21]: So I don't know if we're in or we're out to make it an opt-in or an opt-out type situation.
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, we currently have an opt-in rule, and that rule's not going away.
[SPEAKER_08]: If North Medford wanted to get permit parking on a street, they could do the permit process and do it.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's what we saw several of those last year from this neighborhood on a case-by-case basis.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah, I think it's now time for the citizens of this community, if they're really
[SPEAKER_21]: If this is really something that's important to them, I'd much rather them come to us seeking help versus us continuing to cram these things down on them.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's a lot of work to collect those signatures.
[SPEAKER_21]: I understand that, but at the same time, it's a lot of work for them to collect the signatures to get out of this if there's a strong group out there that doesn't want to be involved in this.
[SPEAKER_21]: So it's a lot of work for them either way.
[SPEAKER_21]: It's a lot of work whether you're supported or you don't support it.
[SPEAKER_21]: So which ones are you siding with or are we siding with the ones who supported the ones we don't.
[SPEAKER_16]: So we could we could be also forcing the hand of coming up with a pilot zone.
[SPEAKER_16]: I mean and getting that ball rolling and then saying that
[SPEAKER_16]: like Alicia said, requesting somebody from the city to say, hey, the proposal now is to start our zone, our zone system, and we'll start with this area.
[SPEAKER_09]: Can I just make just a point, a comment?
[SPEAKER_09]: This is an opportunity from the mayor's office and from the community to have a proactive approach to a potential issue.
[SPEAKER_09]: As you said, alluded to, if it opens and then there's a flood of phone calls, and now we have to go through this process of doing this whole thing, it could take a couple of months.
[SPEAKER_09]: And so now community is sort of suffering from that particular
[SPEAKER_09]: delay, and a delay on this could be catastrophic.
[SPEAKER_09]: The reality is, if a street does not want to be part of the process, they can opt out of this.
[SPEAKER_09]: We're not suggesting that people are ramming anything down a person's throat, but each person has a different need.
[SPEAKER_09]: As a co-chair of the commission on parking policy and process, we actually had over a thousand people talk to us, and specifically the green line was an issue.
[SPEAKER_09]: And as Laura Roomba alluded to, it's within a mile of the station.
[SPEAKER_09]: That is the reality.
[SPEAKER_09]: That's the last mile.
[SPEAKER_09]: That is the study.
[SPEAKER_09]: In addition, the GLX is also looking towards
[SPEAKER_09]: an extension to Route 16.
[SPEAKER_09]: This is something that's not off the table, but this approach allows that to be in place for a future.
[SPEAKER_09]: There's nothing wrong with being proactive.
[SPEAKER_09]: It's important to consider.
[SPEAKER_09]: And this is the first time in the city that we have done something like this because we have a need to do that.
[SPEAKER_09]: And again, as you said, taking that time to do the signatures is just that time and the effort and the once a month opportunity, ordering the signs, getting all of the enforcement people together to ensure that they can effectively do that.
[SPEAKER_09]: So again, I just want you to consider that as well.
[SPEAKER_16]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_16]: Was the recommendation for street by street or zone?
[SPEAKER_16]: My understanding was that it was for zone as opposed to street by street.
[SPEAKER_09]: And that's correct.
[SPEAKER_09]: And that was our recommendation to go through.
[SPEAKER_09]: But this gives an opportunity for people to feel out what works and what doesn't.
[SPEAKER_09]: It gives us an opportunity to speak on this in the future, to see how we can tweak this effectively.
[SPEAKER_09]: But we have the infrastructure in place, being the signage is in place, the enforcement needs are in place, the opportunity for people to get involved and understand how this may work and may not work.
[SPEAKER_09]: But this will give us that zone environment that's related to a transportation district.
[SPEAKER_09]: And we covered that whole area of the potential three stations.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you for the comments and the information.
[SPEAKER_20]: OK, now it's up to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_33]: Chief, can I briefly ask one question?
[SPEAKER_33]: Can I ask for a poll of how many people are for or against the residents that are on this meeting?
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, we we've caused this to public participation and we're going to continue to do this.
[SPEAKER_20]: I mean, one thing I understand, and I appreciate everybody's participation coming tonight, but it is a representation, a representation of the total.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, I think we have to come to some sort of determinations so that we can make a decision tonight and then move forward and make a decision for this.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, as I understand it, I think the commissioners have two sort of feelings on this.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm gonna need to entertain a motion, probably one way or the other, vote it up or down.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'll see if we can second it and then go to another motion.
[SPEAKER_20]: So, Commissioner Brzezinski, I know you have one position.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do you have a motion on your position at which we can- No, I think you just have to stick with the verbiage of 2249.
[SPEAKER_21]: Do we not?
[SPEAKER_21]: You know, whether we approve this?
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't-
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't want to take a counter position.
[SPEAKER_21]: I just want to approve or... No, I motion to table it.
[SPEAKER_08]: I motion to table this debatable.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'll second the motion to table because I think I don't want to lose it for six months because I'd like to gather more information and then consider it either for denial or approval the next time.
[SPEAKER_20]: I was just debating with my team here whether or not a motion to table is a non-debatable issue, but it will set itself before we can do that.
[SPEAKER_20]: So the motion on the floor by Commissioner Hunt is to table 2022-49, seconded by Commissioner McGiven.
[SPEAKER_20]: Alba, on the roll call.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_15]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Passaciuolo?
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_21]: Can I comment or just vote?
[SPEAKER_20]: Vote.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'll allow you to comment after.
[SPEAKER_21]: No.
[SPEAKER_20]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: 421-2022-49 tabled.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner Buzzynski?
[SPEAKER_20]: Being in government is tough.
[SPEAKER_21]: You're never going to make everybody happy, but you've got to make decisions.
[SPEAKER_21]: And we've just not made another decision on something that's incredibly important.
[SPEAKER_21]: So that's all.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you, sir.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, so that item was tabled.
[SPEAKER_20]: It is 6.33.
[SPEAKER_20]: I know that a number of folks have to, at least myself, I'm gonna have to head out of here in about 12 minutes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant Harold McGilvery will take over as chair in my absence.
[SPEAKER_20]: so that we can maintain a quorum despite anything else.
[SPEAKER_20]: Is Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Tiberi back yet?
[SPEAKER_20]: Did she log on yet?
[SPEAKER_20]: Do we know, can we see her?
[SPEAKER_20]: She said she was on hold for a while.
[SPEAKER_29]: I'm back on.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, so stand by one second.
[SPEAKER_20]: Back to return to new business 2022-41 Handicap Parking Sign in the yellow Tiberi 37th Street.
[SPEAKER_20]: Alva, is the paperwork in order?
[SPEAKER_20]: All of everything has been passed in?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_22]: And Sergeant Rogers visited with the family and he has made his recommendations passed on to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_20]: And before I get to Sergeant Rogers, Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Tiberi, the floor is yours.
[SPEAKER_20]: If you want to present your petition for the Handicap Parking Sign.
[SPEAKER_29]: It's just, I said earlier, there's a mobility issue with both mom and dad along driveway.
[SPEAKER_29]: So it'd be easier for them to park right in the front.
[SPEAKER_29]: In fact, my dad had been parking there and I have moved out of Medford for quite some time.
[SPEAKER_29]: And I didn't realize that a sticker was involved.
[SPEAKER_29]: He got a ticket too, that I'm trying to, I don't know if this is the place to appeal that or this is not the place.
[SPEAKER_20]: Unfortunately, it is not the place, but thank you for the presentation.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioners, any questions, comments?
[SPEAKER_20]: Actually, let's hear from Sergeant Rogers, who went out and visited with the family and the location.
[SPEAKER_20]: Chief, like Mr. Berry said, I met with her mother and father.
[SPEAKER_20]: They both have handicapped placards.
[SPEAKER_20]: I don't know the commission's aware this is right at the end of 7th Street, where Bianchi's Sausage is located.
[SPEAKER_20]: There's numerous trucks that are parking there.
[SPEAKER_20]: Numerous trucks parked in front of the house.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_20]: And the space would be right in front of the stairs.
[SPEAKER_20]: They could go directly into the house.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you, Sergeant.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioners, any questions, concerns?
[SPEAKER_08]: No, I was just looking, it looks like one of their neighbors already has a handicaps nearby.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was just trying to find it to understand it.
[SPEAKER_29]: It's nowhere near my parents' home, I don't believe.
[SPEAKER_29]: Huh.
[SPEAKER_29]: And she- I mistyped 37.
[SPEAKER_08]: Sorry, when I searched 37th Street, it put me, that's the one we're looking at, right?
[SPEAKER_08]: It put me in the middle of the block, not at the end of the block.
[SPEAKER_08]: I was just trying to make sure I understood what the location was we were approving.
[SPEAKER_31]: Any other commissioners, comments, questions, concerns?
[SPEAKER_20]: Are there any neighbors or someone from the public who wishes to speak for or against the petition?
[SPEAKER_20]: Again, I do see both Pat Barry and Chrissy Salvato with their hands up.
[SPEAKER_20]: If you wish to speak to this, go ahead, but if not, just, if you could put your hands down, it would help me tremendously.
[SPEAKER_16]: I got a quick question, Chief.
[SPEAKER_16]: The driveway, does this house have a driveway and is the idea to have the,
[SPEAKER_16]: location in front of the stairs, is that what we're getting at here?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, Tim, the driveway to the right, it is some kind of, it's not that far of a distance for someone like us, but for an elderly couple to walk to the down the driveway, sidewalk and up the stairs.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do I have a motion from Commissioner?
[SPEAKER_20]: I'll make a motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_20]: A motion of Commissioner McGiven to approve.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_20]: Second.
[SPEAKER_20]: Seconded by Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_20]: Roll call vote, Alba.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastororo?
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, five, nothing.
[SPEAKER_20]: The motion is approved.
[SPEAKER_20]: Mr. Berry, I appreciate your patience tonight and your participation and thank you for, and I'm glad to go home safely and we're able to log back in and get the issue resolved.
[SPEAKER_29]: Thank you so much.
[SPEAKER_29]: I appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_29]: I can log off now, correct?
[SPEAKER_29]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, thanks.
[SPEAKER_20]: 2022-42 Handicap Hockensang, Rosalia Lodato, 9 Wareham Street.
[SPEAKER_20]: First question, Alba, is all the paperwork in order for the petitioner?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, Chief.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, is the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_20]: Let me just make sure to see if the... I believe I, yep, I believe I see her.
[SPEAKER_20]: Can you unmute yourself, Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Lodato?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Welcome, and if you would like to say a few words in support of the petition?
[SPEAKER_28]: Yes, I am handicapped, and my street is Wayham Street, and it's always busy.
[SPEAKER_28]: When I come home, I have to go park halfway up the street and walk down.
[SPEAKER_28]: I do have a driveway, but it's not my driveway to park.
[SPEAKER_28]: And I would like an handicapped pole right in front of my house, so it's easier for me to go up my stairs and go right in.
[SPEAKER_28]: My street is very, very busy.
[SPEAKER_28]: Everybody parks on the street.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant Rogers, did you visit on Wareham Street?
[SPEAKER_20]: I did.
[SPEAKER_20]: I believe I spoke to her son or son-in-law, Chief.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: And reiterate what Lodato said.
[SPEAKER_20]: I would request to approve.
[SPEAKER_08]: Can I just confirm, because this doesn't actually say it, that you do have a handicapped placard, because if we put a handicapped spot, you have to have that placard.
[SPEAKER_28]: Yes, yes, I do.
[SPEAKER_28]: Yes, I do.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, other questions, comments from the commissioners?
[SPEAKER_20]: Do I have a motion?
[SPEAKER_21]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm sorry, who's that?
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_20]: Motion by Commissioner Brzezinski on approval.
[SPEAKER_20]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_30]: A second.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioner Passatoro.
[SPEAKER_20]: Roll call vote, Alba, please.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGibbon.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Passatoro.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Chief Buckley?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes, on a 5-0 vote, the motion is approved.
[SPEAKER_20]: I'm going to take one minute.
[SPEAKER_20]: I think this is probably the time that I have to head out.
[SPEAKER_20]: I want to thank everybody for tonight and appreciate their patience, understanding, but especially their participation in this process.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant McGillivray will take over as chair, as my designee, and hopefully the meeting continues as planned.
[SPEAKER_20]: Smoothly, smoothly as it has, and I'm off to the city council.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you and I apologize for that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Good night.
[SPEAKER_30]: Good night.
20, 22, 48.
[SPEAKER_22]: 48, we're going?
[SPEAKER_22]: Mm-hmm.
[SPEAKER_22]: What happened?
[SPEAKER_22]: No, 43.
[SPEAKER_22]: Oh, 43?
[SPEAKER_19]: No, we're just doing the end of family.
[SPEAKER_19]: Oh, is that all we're doing?
[SPEAKER_22]: Wait, we are?
[SPEAKER_22]: to do take the handicap.
[SPEAKER_19]: You want to take a motion to take it out of order?
[SPEAKER_22]: Do you want to stay in our regular business?
[SPEAKER_19]: You have to.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_22]: I thought they were doing all the individuals, but I think you're right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah, we need a motion to take it out of order.
[SPEAKER_19]: Unless somebody wants to make a motion.
[SPEAKER_22]: No, no, no, leave it like it is.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right, 2022-43 permit parking variance for Brackett Street from Jacqueline Judith, 60 Elm Street.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is all the paperwork in on that, Alba?
[SPEAKER_13]: And is the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_13]: Hi, I'm here to support her petition.
[SPEAKER_13]: My name is David Ellsworth.
[SPEAKER_13]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: Could we ask the petitioner, so normally if somebody's asking for a parking variance, it's to park around the corner.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm aware, I'm under the impression that this area only has permit parking from Memorial Day to Labor Day, and 60 Elm Street is quite a distance from Brackett Street.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I wanted to better understand this request.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yeah, I believe the confusion was that there is no ability to obtain guest parking passes for anywhere around the residence.
[SPEAKER_13]: I think the preference was it's either Equavia or Aquavia, which is a private way.
[SPEAKER_13]: And I believe the secondary preference was Brackett, which is the closest street with potentially parking there is.
[SPEAKER_13]: So we're looking to figure out where we can get guest parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: Todd, are you or somebody able to confirm is this regular permit parking on Brackett or is it just seasonal?
[SPEAKER_08]: Did we lose Todd?
[SPEAKER_32]: Todd's still on.
[SPEAKER_32]: He's muted.
[SPEAKER_32]: What was the question?
[SPEAKER_08]: Does Brackett have regular permit parking or isn't it just seasonal?
[SPEAKER_33]: I'd have to look at the records, but typically near Wrights Pond, it's usually seasonal, but I'll check.
[SPEAKER_08]: I'm looking at the sign online.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, it's Memorial Day to Labor Day is the permit parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: So nobody needs a guest permit to park there for 10 months of the year.
[SPEAKER_08]: So you're just looking for something for the summers then.
[SPEAKER_13]: If that is the case, then yes.
[SPEAKER_13]: And also with a quick follow-up question afterwards about resident parking as well, as I wanted to make sure that for whatever parking variance this is, if it also applies to resident permit as well.
[SPEAKER_08]: So, right, my understanding of what you're asking for is a resident permit.
[SPEAKER_08]: and that comes with guest permits, I think.
[SPEAKER_08]: Actually, Alva, can you clarify that?
[SPEAKER_08]: If you get a variance, usually it doesn't get guest permits.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes, correct.
[SPEAKER_22]: The variance just comes for a sticker with the vehicle, no visitor passes.
[SPEAKER_08]: So this doesn't solve his problem at all, because he wants guest permits for Brackett Street.
[SPEAKER_22]: That's what he was, she, the lady, was requesting.
[SPEAKER_22]: I believe
[SPEAKER_22]: They have a driveway that can accommodate her car.
[SPEAKER_22]: It's just the visitor passes they were requesting because nobody can park on Elm Street.
[SPEAKER_08]: Do we have a mechanism to allow visitor guest or guest passes through a variance?
[SPEAKER_08]: Like, is that allowed under our rules?
[SPEAKER_22]: It has to be voted on by the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_08]: So we have the authority to allow it.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: We have done it in the past.
[SPEAKER_22]: I can't recall.
[SPEAKER_22]: It's been not many, few, but people have been granted visitor passes.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't really have a problem with
[SPEAKER_08]: Granting, so the request here is not what's written on the agenda is permit parking variants, but what they want is guest parking permit variants for Brackett Street.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes, yes, Commissioner Hunt, that is correct.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I just wanna make sure that if we vote for this, we're voting for the correct thing, which is not what's written on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_22]: Correct, it is for visitor passes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Can we verify from David Ellsworth if there is a driveway and that she does park her car in that driveway and the visitor passes are the only problem?
[SPEAKER_13]: I have two bits of information for that.
[SPEAKER_13]: Yes, there's a driveway and she is in the process of getting her change of address form from R&B so that way she can get her permit parking.
[SPEAKER_13]: The issue that we have is that her residents soon will have construction done which will remove access to the driveway due to removing some pipes with lead in them in the front yard.
[SPEAKER_13]: Regardless of that, that's part of the information for the variance in my second question of once she applies for a parking permit, will she have to go through this process for the parking permit variance as well for the same street?
[SPEAKER_08]: Right.
[SPEAKER_08]: Well, because that's what's actually on here is the parking permit variance request, not the guest permit.
[SPEAKER_08]: Like the words on the agenda say permit parking variance.
[SPEAKER_13]: And even still, I think my hope is essentially to apply to essentially both, right?
[SPEAKER_13]: As she will soon not have a driveway because of things like construction.
[SPEAKER_13]: So wondering if we can get a precedence for where she can park based on that fact coming up.
[SPEAKER_08]: Right.
[SPEAKER_08]: So first of all, I just want you to know in the short run, she can park on Brackett Street now because it's only permit parking during the summer months.
[SPEAKER_08]: So there's no reason why she couldn't park over there this week.
[SPEAKER_08]: Is that clear?
[SPEAKER_08]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_13]: And for the summer months?
[SPEAKER_08]: Just for next summer, she wants a variance to be able to park over there.
[SPEAKER_13]: I would say correct based on that information.
[SPEAKER_19]: Why don't we wait until the petition is present and take this matter up with the petition of presence?
[SPEAKER_19]: We table this or just vote it down and have her reapply.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right.
[SPEAKER_22]: We have to table it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Table it.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion table.
[SPEAKER_22]: Second.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_22]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Who made the motion?
[SPEAKER_19]: Mr. McGiven made the motion and Commissioner Hunt seconded it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGiven.
[SPEAKER_16]: Yes, sorry.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Passacoro?
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGilvrey?
[SPEAKER_19]: There's nothing on this table.
[SPEAKER_19]: So Mr. Ellsworth, we'll bring this back up next month and just make sure that Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Judith is here so we can address it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Right now it doesn't matter because Labor Day is over.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we have plenty of time.
[SPEAKER_13]: In the meantime, for guest parking, she has no options until- No, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_08]: Guests can park on bracket.
[SPEAKER_08]: Anybody can park on bracket now.
[SPEAKER_13]: Do you have any permits or things to put in the car?
[SPEAKER_08]: Nope, nothing.
[SPEAKER_13]: Very good, thank you.
[SPEAKER_13]: It expires on Labor Day.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: 2022-44, 15 minute parking sign.
[SPEAKER_19]: in front of Ronnie's Place, 433 Salem Street.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_19]: Anybody from Ronnie's Place present?
[SPEAKER_08]: Somebody's, Melissa Hall's raising her hand.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sorry, this isn't for this petition.
[SPEAKER_07]: I raised my hand before.
[SPEAKER_07]: I apologize for coming late to the meeting.
[SPEAKER_07]: I had work.
[SPEAKER_07]: I did submit a petition.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'm not sure if you guys have gone over it yet or not, or if I'm
[SPEAKER_07]: in the lineup for later on.
[SPEAKER_07]: What's the address?
[SPEAKER_07]: The address is 262 Main Street in Medford.
[SPEAKER_08]: We haven't gotten there yet.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay, no problem.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'll wait.
[SPEAKER_07]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: A 22-44, 15 minute parking in front of Ronnie's place.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is anybody from Ronnie's place present, petitioner?
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant, I did go down there.
[SPEAKER_20]: I spoke to, I believe the owner of Ronnie's and he's requesting, there was a sign about 10 feet further down to our parking and he's requesting a 15 minute sign for pickup to go.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioners.
[SPEAKER_08]: We've approved this for a number of businesses that work on that quick pickup model.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't see any reason not to approve this one too.
[SPEAKER_19]: Any other comments from any other commissioners?
[SPEAKER_21]: I seem to remember that the last one we approved was for Alamo and he joined the meeting.
[SPEAKER_21]: So I don't know why the Ronnie's people aren't here to kind of talk to us about the need for this.
[SPEAKER_22]: Does he want to table it?
[SPEAKER_19]: Well, again, do you want to, we can either vote on the motion or we can either vote on this as is or we can make a motion to table it and ask somebody from Ronnie's place to be present next month.
[SPEAKER_08]: And I would just say that it's clear that his, his location is his business is a pickup model.
[SPEAKER_08]: He's not a dining model restaurant.
[SPEAKER_08]: Um, originally when we did, when we started the 15 minute program, we just brought a list of them that had requested them.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioners with what's your pleasure.
[SPEAKER_19]: You want to make a, you want to vote on this as is, or do you want to make a motion to table it?
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm familiar with the spot directly.
[SPEAKER_16]: I mean, I wouldn't, I would motion to approve this one.
[SPEAKER_19]: I have a motion to approve as is second.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: So Mr. Commissioner given the motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioner Hunt with the second roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGiven?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pezzatura?
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_19]: No.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_33]: Sorry, I just had a point of clarification.
[SPEAKER_33]: Today, most of these 15 minutes a free 15 minutes just wanted to point that out so I don't know if that was what folks are approving or not.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's great point.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do we need to add that.
[SPEAKER_19]: No, we didn't for Alamo.
[SPEAKER_19]: We did not for Alamo, okay.
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't remember it being free 15 minute at all.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just remember that there was 15 minute parking.
[SPEAKER_08]: We started it during the pandemic.
[SPEAKER_19]: The assumption would be it's 15 minutes is for free, correct?
[SPEAKER_33]: There's, there's free 15 minutes for Dunkin' Donuts across the street in front of Comfort Delivery Place.
[SPEAKER_33]: There's free 15 minute in West Metro in front of the pizza shop.
[SPEAKER_33]: So there are some, and then the temporary ones, I don't know if they specified it, but I think that was the understanding.
[SPEAKER_16]: It's what I thought I was voting on free 15.
[SPEAKER_16]: All right.
[SPEAKER_08]: It's frankly, our meter system right now requires you to pay for an hour if you pay for 15 minutes.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I would rather give them free 15 minutes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, go on.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, that motion passed.
[SPEAKER_19]: Four in the affirmative, one in the negative.
[SPEAKER_19]: Next, 2022-45, Lisa Reneau of Stearns Ave, to replace old slow children's sign and request two additional signs.
[SPEAKER_19]: Does the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_19]: Is there anybody from Stearns Ave present?
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant if I could speak, I did go down there.
[SPEAKER_20]: The one sign that there is completely unreadable.
[SPEAKER_20]: It's completely faded.
[SPEAKER_20]: And if the commissioners want to add two more signs.
[SPEAKER_20]: Commissioners.
[SPEAKER_08]: We've discussed this in the past, that that language is dated.
[SPEAKER_08]: that we would put like caution children at play, something like that.
[SPEAKER_08]: Do we have a standard now, Todd or Tim?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, the slow sign, the rectangular is kind of outdated.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so normally warning signs of the diamond variety and some other language like that or similar would probably be more appropriate.
[SPEAKER_33]: But I think since the warning sign, it doesn't really even need to be voted on in my opinion, but it's not a regulatory sign, if that helps.
[SPEAKER_08]: That's what I was thinking too.
[SPEAKER_08]: I didn't think that we needed to vote on them.
[SPEAKER_08]: In fact, the only time I've ever discussed these signs was in a different commission meeting where we were getting a business to put in the signs for free for us that said something about caution children at play.
[SPEAKER_08]: And if they want caution children at play signs, I'm fine with it or whatever the right language is.
[SPEAKER_08]: I just prefer not the literal word slow children.
[SPEAKER_16]: We can refer this to highway division.
[SPEAKER_08]: Can we do that?
[SPEAKER_16]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_08]: Motion to refer to the highway division for review and appropriate signage, signage as appropriate.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second.
[SPEAKER_19]: Here we have, get that elbow.
[SPEAKER_31]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: On, on that motion to refer 20
[SPEAKER_19]: 22-45 to the highway department to provide appropriate signage for Stearns Ave.
[SPEAKER_19]: All those in favor, roll call vote, please.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner McGibbon.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Hunt.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Professor Chorow.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGilvrey.
[SPEAKER_19]: Five in the affirmative, none in the negative, that motion passes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Next motion 2022-46, request for a no parking here to corner on Greenleaf Avenue at Brookings Street from Megan Bennett, 70 Greenleaf Avenue.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Bennett present?
[SPEAKER_25]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_25]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_19]: You got the floor.
[SPEAKER_25]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_25]: I wanted to request this because I live right on the corner of Greenleaf Avenue and Brookings Street,
[SPEAKER_25]: And where I am, we are right off of George street.
[SPEAKER_25]: So that's a main road and cars, emergency vehicles, especially when there are cars parked on each corner, it is impossible for vehicle for emergency vehicles to get down there because there's not, I don't think that the rule of
[SPEAKER_25]: 20 feet from the intersection is widely known and it doesn't, it's, it's difficult to enforce because sometimes, I mean, I can call or I can submit a C to click fix.
[SPEAKER_25]: And then by the time that somebody gets there, then they might be gone.
[SPEAKER_25]: And also I can't, I can't submit a C click fix or call when there's already an emergency vehicle trying to get down our street and can't make the turn.
[SPEAKER_25]: So that's why I was, I requested a no parking here to corner sign.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: Anybody else here?
[SPEAKER_08]: Could Todd or somebody please clarify?
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't understand where this sign would go.
[SPEAKER_19]: I was going to ask Todd to pull it up.
[SPEAKER_08]: Before people comment on it, it would be really helpful to understand exactly what we're talking about.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant, if I could explain, I did go down there.
[SPEAKER_20]: Going down Brookings, turning right onto Greenleaf, it was extremely congested.
[SPEAKER_20]: I believe, Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Bennett, a fire truck could not make the turn a couple of days before that, trying to get down Greenleaf from Bennett.
[SPEAKER_20]: So I believe, Todd, that, and Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Bennett, if I'm wrong, going down Brookings, taking you right on Greenleaf, you'd want the sign right there.
[SPEAKER_08]: on Greenleaf on the right hand side of the street?
[SPEAKER_25]: On Greenleaf, either on the right hand of the street in front of my house and across the street if possible, because if there are cars parked on both, even on just one corner, it's extremely difficult to make the turn.
[SPEAKER_25]: Like there've been times when the trash trucks could not take the turn.
[SPEAKER_25]: They'd have to circle down and... There it is.
[SPEAKER_32]: So which corner here?
[SPEAKER_25]: The next, um, yep.
[SPEAKER_25]: Right over there.
[SPEAKER_25]: Right.
[SPEAKER_25]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_25]: Right there in front of the Brown house.
[SPEAKER_25]: And then right there.
[SPEAKER_25]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_25]: Right there.
[SPEAKER_25]: And then directly across the street in front of my house, the white house.
[SPEAKER_25]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_08]: So I guess I do wonder if the neighbors who across the street, that Brown and tan house, are they aware that this is on the agenda tonight that it's being discussed?
[SPEAKER_08]: I don't know that.
[SPEAKER_25]: Um, the, that house does have, um, there are owners who live there, but there are also, it's also, yes, of a rental unit.
[SPEAKER_25]: So I don't know.
[SPEAKER_25]: I don't know if they know anything about it.
[SPEAKER_25]: I assume that they must've gotten a letter about it.
[SPEAKER_33]: Um, may may, uh, sergeant may speak for a second.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yes, sure.
[SPEAKER_33]: So I would just like to point out, if as the resident requested 20 foot rules, some people aren't aware of it.
[SPEAKER_33]: So is the residents request just to sign the 20 feet.
[SPEAKER_33]: If that's the case, then there's actually no regulation to be voted on and it could be just referred to DPW.
[SPEAKER_33]: If it's beyond the 20 feet, then it should require traffic commission.
[SPEAKER_08]: Are you able to tell us, like, is that, you see on the left, the sidewalk changes from white to tan?
[SPEAKER_08]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_08]: Is that 20?
[SPEAKER_08]: Todd, can you give us an idea where would the sign go if it was 20 feet?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, let me just, I'm gonna use my other screen to measure at the same time.
[SPEAKER_19]: How many steps, Todd?
[SPEAKER_33]: For me or for others?
[SPEAKER_08]: Ma'am, just so you know, there's no automatic notification of the abutters of things like this.
[SPEAKER_25]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_25]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_25]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_25]: I got, um, I got the, the only reason I knew about this being on the agenda was because I got, um, I got, we got the letter addressed.
[SPEAKER_25]: Like it wasn't addressed to myself.
[SPEAKER_25]: It was addressed to like residents.
[SPEAKER_25]: I don't know if, um, I don't know if anybody downstairs from me got it either.
[SPEAKER_25]: I forgot to ask.
[SPEAKER_25]: That was, that's, that's my fault.
[SPEAKER_33]: Sorry, I'm trying to... What's a sidewalk panel, about four feet?
[SPEAKER_33]: Sidewalk panels are usually four or five feet, yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: But usually I would measure from the projected edge, so right here.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it's... Let me just... I think probably in front of that red car.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm counting four.
[SPEAKER_19]: to that red car.
[SPEAKER_19]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'd like to refer this to the fire department anyway, and get their comment on it.
[SPEAKER_16]: I don't wanna put up signs for the 20 foot rule if they want 30 for their trucks.
[SPEAKER_16]: I would rather base our action off of recommendation from the fire department more than anything else.
[SPEAKER_19]: Wanna make a motion on this?
[SPEAKER_19]: to refer to the fire department for the next meeting?
[SPEAKER_16]: Yeah, I'd like to make a motion to refer to the fire department for advisement for the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_22]: Approving it, but refer to the fire department for the distance of posting.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, so Alva's recommendation would be to approve this with the caveat that it goes to the fire department.
[SPEAKER_19]: for a recommendation if more distances are needed.
[SPEAKER_33]: Looks like 20 feet is about here.
[SPEAKER_33]: One pin will be on the greater white.
[SPEAKER_16]: All right, I'll make a motion to approve under the advisement of the fire department for the offset.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do I have a second on that motion?
[SPEAKER_19]: Second.
[SPEAKER_04]: I wanted to speak on this if I could.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, who's that?
[SPEAKER_19]: Who's that?
[SPEAKER_08]: Probably the resident with her hand up, Eunice.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Hi, thanks very much.
[SPEAKER_04]: I live, as I stated earlier, on Greenleaf as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you bring your little cursor down to the Greenleaf-Benham section there, I am down there.
[SPEAKER_04]: there at 46 and 48 Greenleaf and having very similar problems to Megan.
[SPEAKER_04]: I'm in the greenhouse there, Hunter Greenhouse.
[SPEAKER_04]: Similar problems to where the Medford Fire Department has trouble getting through, Trash Truck has trouble getting through.
[SPEAKER_04]: Currently, I have parked next door to me at
[SPEAKER_04]: 40, 52, 54 for the past couple of months, a white van, he's been ticketed twice, that is consistently hanging over the curb from Benham to Greenleaf.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you see where the telephone pole is right there, right, yeah, right there.
[SPEAKER_04]: He's parked in front of that hanging over the curb.
[SPEAKER_04]: And so it makes,
[SPEAKER_04]: any turn for anybody, you know, especially our first responders, pretty difficult.
[SPEAKER_04]: And then going back to, as I stated earlier,
[SPEAKER_04]: Um, there's no way to tell, uh, this particular van, and it's got a companion van as well that's been parking on, uh, Benham.
[SPEAKER_04]: They have Florida plates.
[SPEAKER_04]: So they're, you know, certainly not, um, you know, part of the permit parking plan.
[SPEAKER_04]: Um, and, but even if, if they had mass plates, there would be no way to know without the window sticker, whether they belonged or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: Um, Greenleaf parking is just, you know,
[SPEAKER_04]: We got permit parking about a year and a half ago because we had problems with Tufts students leaving their cars on the street all the time.
[SPEAKER_04]: So it was not to pay for parking up at Tufts.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's gotten a little bit better since we got permit parking, but it's still a problem.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's still a mess.
[SPEAKER_04]: We have obviously more cars than we have spaces, but without the parking stickers,
[SPEAKER_04]: can't tell who belongs and who doesn't, people are parking across driveways, people are parking too close to the curb, so as to fit as many cars in as possible.
[SPEAKER_16]: I think you're bringing up a lot of good things, Eunice, but are you in support of the action that's on the table?
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_16]: Okay, and I think, I think, and I'm sorry if I'm speaking out of term, Harry here but it just, we have it sounds like we have a documented issue with a fire truck having an issue at the corner that's on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_16]: So if there are other documented egress issues for the fire department.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm hoping that they will, they will put it on the agenda.
[SPEAKER_16]: and moving forward.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'd like to see that from the fire department, just because I'm not going to take hearsay.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm not saying you're lying, Eunice.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'm just saying that everybody could say that police vehicles or fire department vehicles have issues with turning movements.
[SPEAKER_16]: I'd rather get that information directly from the fire department if we can.
[SPEAKER_04]: Oh, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_04]: If it means actually restricting cars to 30 feet instead of 20 feet, that's even better.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Um, anybody else from Greenleaf out here that wants to speak on this?
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_22]: Um, we have a motion.
[SPEAKER_19]: We have a motion from, uh, commissioner McGiven.
[SPEAKER_19]: It was seconded by commissioner hunt.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do we want to take, do we want to repeat that?
[SPEAKER_19]: Does everybody remember what that motion was to approve this upon recommendation for the recommendation from the fire department?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner given.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_31]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay that's five in the affirmative no negatives that motion passes and myself and Sergeant Rogers will advise the traffic units to go down there and enforce
[SPEAKER_19]: all the parking violations down there that don't relate to resident parking, because as we all know, the police department doesn't have the technology right now to handle the resident park.
[SPEAKER_16]: And yeah, Sergeant, I'm gonna have to excuse myself, it's that time, so.
[SPEAKER_08]: Yeah, sorry, I have to go down to the city council meeting as well, I apologize.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, next 2022-47 permit pack and variants for a Ken boy, I can one day five sherbet court apartment number four for both street is the petitioner present.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yep, I'm here.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: You want to tell us what's going on.
[SPEAKER_10]: Yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_10]: So I'm a, as of September 1, I'm a new resident of Medford.
[SPEAKER_10]: I live at the 5 and 6 Sherborne Court Apartments.
[SPEAKER_10]: They currently don't apply to Medford permanent parking, and I am requesting a permanent parking variance to park on one of the side streets that does have that available.
[SPEAKER_22]: That would be Bow Street.
[SPEAKER_22]: Bow Street.
[SPEAKER_21]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_21]: Didn't we have this come up a couple meetings ago someone else who lived in this apartment who was seeking.
[SPEAKER_21]: You're right.
[SPEAKER_21]: Talking on bow.
[SPEAKER_32]: So this is the dead end here and pose right here.
[SPEAKER_21]: For some reason or another we weren't that she wasn't able to park on Strathmore she wasn't able to park on brave more.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yeah, all those side streets are full.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is Bow Street full?
[SPEAKER_22]: No, Bow Street is available.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah, I think that was the discussion we had on this issue again a couple of meetings ago, maybe three meetings ago with the same resident of this apartment complex.
[SPEAKER_19]: Any other commentary from commissioners?
[SPEAKER_30]: Is it an apartment building?
[SPEAKER_35]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_30]: And they don't give any parking for the residents?
[SPEAKER_10]: They do have some paid parking, limited paid parking, yeah.
[SPEAKER_10]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: The address wasn't mentioned?
[SPEAKER_20]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, it's the apartment buildings on Broadway.
[SPEAKER_19]: On Broadway, but it's in Medford on Broadway.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: A motion to approve this variance.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion to approve the variance.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_22]: I'll second.
[SPEAKER_19]: I have a second.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastororo.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes, Mr. Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Dr. McGillivray?
[SPEAKER_22]: Three to nothing, two absent.
[SPEAKER_19]: Two absent, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, 2022-48, Handicap Hockensheim, Michael McConnell, 105 Brookings Street.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is the petitioner present?
[SPEAKER_17]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_17]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_17]: Aye, thank you.
[SPEAKER_17]: I have a placket and my problem is that we have a shared driver with our neighbor.
[SPEAKER_17]: And when they park their SUV in the driveway, it's very hard for me to get out.
[SPEAKER_17]: I had both hips replaced and they want to do my knees now, but I'm not really ready for it.
[SPEAKER_17]: So it'd be easier for me to park in front of my house and just go up the stairs.
[SPEAKER_20]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant Rogers?
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant, I'm just reiterating what Miss McConnell said.
[SPEAKER_20]: I did go down.
[SPEAKER_20]: To the left of the house is a shared driveway.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, there were numerous cars in the driveway.
[SPEAKER_20]: Um, he could park right in front of this house, go right up the stairs into the house.
[SPEAKER_20]: I would, uh, request approval.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: Anybody else from, uh, working street present?
[SPEAKER_39]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_39]: Hello.
[SPEAKER_39]: My name is Patricia hatch.
[SPEAKER_39]: I live at one Oh seven working street, and I am in favor of this because I am one of the neighbors that is, um, impacted by this.
[SPEAKER_39]: Definitely.
[SPEAKER_39]: Mr. McConnell, um, has some,
[SPEAKER_39]: mobility issues, and it would definitely be much, much easier for him.
[SPEAKER_39]: He's often had to park all the way down the street and carrying groceries and things of that nature.
[SPEAKER_39]: So as you can see, we share the driveway with 109.
[SPEAKER_39]: So if you could approve this, I think it would be a great thing.
[SPEAKER_39]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioners?
[SPEAKER_30]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't think this one gets any better.
[SPEAKER_21]: The neighbor likes it.
[SPEAKER_21]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Can I have a motion to approve?
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion by Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do I have a second?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, we have a second.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastororo?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Approved.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_19]: Approved.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Mcgillivray?
[SPEAKER_19]: Three.
[SPEAKER_22]: Nothing, two absent.
[SPEAKER_19]: The two absent, motion passes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Good luck.
[SPEAKER_19]: 2022-50 request from Thomas Barry, 228 Grove Street for a speed table between 238 to 260 Grove Street.
[SPEAKER_14]: Present.
[SPEAKER_14]: Aye.
[SPEAKER_14]: I requested a speed table due to the high rate of speed that cars come around the corner
[SPEAKER_14]: coming from the Winchester side of Grove Street.
[SPEAKER_14]: I live right by the back exit of the cemetery.
[SPEAKER_14]: I live at 228.
[SPEAKER_14]: There's 19 small children in the small area that I live between Holland Circle, Apache Circle, Collins, and Grove.
[SPEAKER_14]: There are 19 kids under the age of 12.
[SPEAKER_14]: a bunch of pedestrians in and out of the cemetery, and a large number of bikers in and out of the cemetery.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's very difficult for them to cross the street.
[SPEAKER_14]: There's no sidewalk on the other side of Grove Street for anybody to walk on.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's all grass.
[SPEAKER_14]: So coming out of the cemetery is difficult.
[SPEAKER_14]: And obviously, just general kids being out playing is also an issue.
[SPEAKER_14]: High range of speed coming around the corner.
[SPEAKER_14]: So that's my request.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is there anybody else from Grove Street on the call that wants to comment on this, for or against it?
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant, if I could comment.
[SPEAKER_20]: and I want the commissioners know this has been a long ongoing problem up on Grove Street.
[SPEAKER_20]: We've had speed trailers up there.
[SPEAKER_20]: We've had our officers doing radar up there.
[SPEAKER_20]: I would maybe ask for Todd's input on this to see what else we can do to make it safer.
[SPEAKER_19]: Director Blake.
[SPEAKER_33]: You're muted.
[SPEAKER_33]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, we're aware of a number of locations in the city that, you know, experienced speeding.
[SPEAKER_33]: This is one of them.
[SPEAKER_33]: As everyone knows we did do a speed table in the lower section of Grove.
[SPEAKER_33]: But, you know, we, we would like to put them everywhere that needs them but we don't have the resources to do so.
[SPEAKER_33]: The good news is the city applied for a grant with the state to do traffic calming various locations throughout the city.
[SPEAKER_33]: And this was one of the areas targeted.
[SPEAKER_33]: identified in that grant application that we have got approved for.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, in that particular proposal.
[SPEAKER_33]: It didn't necessarily include the speed tables again resource wise even when we get grants.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's tough to put them everywhere that we want to, or everywhere that may need it.
[SPEAKER_33]: But in this particular case the proposal is to add.
[SPEAKER_33]: bike lanes to narrow the roadway, but also to add radar feedback signs, which have been somewhat reasonably effective in other areas.
[SPEAKER_33]: They're not necessarily the same, we realize, as raised elements, but radar feedback signs in this area, I think, would be helpful.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so that's one thing that's coming up in terms of improvements for that particular area.
[SPEAKER_19]: So do we have the funding.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we have, we got awarded a.
[SPEAKER_33]: a grant related to speed control speed management, but it doesn't necessarily afford us, even though we got that grant, it doesn't necessarily afford us to put raised elements in all places in the city we'd like to.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it includes a wide variety.
[SPEAKER_33]: It does include some speed tables and some radar feedback signs and some other elements.
[SPEAKER_33]: For this particular segment of the city, it includes bike lanes and radar feedback signs, not a speed table.
[SPEAKER_33]: Okay, Commissioner, there is opportunity to, you know, speak with the community about these treatments but again, it's been my experience that most streets experience and issues all want raised elements and we, we don't necessarily the resources that even when we get grants so we would like to and we're striving to improve wherever we can.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it was a big win to get this but you know won't necessarily give everyone exactly what they want everywhere.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, director Blake commissioners.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is there a list of hotspots that we kind of let the police department know about?
[SPEAKER_21]: I understand that there's been resources allocated to this in the past, but it seems like it's still a problem where there's still, you know, can we increase police presence up there for a while?
[SPEAKER_21]: I'd be hesitant to actually approve improvements to an area that's actually going to then be improved.
[SPEAKER_21]: in the not-too-distant future.
[SPEAKER_21]: So I like the speed tables in certain instances.
[SPEAKER_21]: There are a couple other ones on Grove already, but I don't want to approve something, and then we're just going to add something else to it shortly down the road.
[SPEAKER_14]: The other speed table's at 69 Grove.
[SPEAKER_14]: It's a half a mile from the area that I'm suggesting.
[SPEAKER_21]: I unfortunately walk in your area a lot, and I do experience the Frogger-type experience when you cross the road there.
[SPEAKER_21]: I'm thinking increased police presence in that area may be an alternative to allocating city resources to raising the road for new speed tables.
[SPEAKER_19]: We can do our best with the increased police presence.
[SPEAKER_19]: In a perfect world, yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Things come up and sometimes when we're trying to commit to an area, we end up having to
[SPEAKER_19]: other calls that come in.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we will do our best to get the offices down there running radar.
[SPEAKER_19]: Um, but the people on grocery see us down there.
[SPEAKER_19]: They, they know that we're down there, but we're not down there all the time with, we just don't have the, uh, the, the, the resources to have somebody down there every single shift.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's, we'll do the best we can.
[SPEAKER_19]: Any other comments?
[SPEAKER_14]: Should I try to get more support from my neighborhood?
[SPEAKER_19]: I can tell you this, every neighborhood in the city wants raised speed tables.
[SPEAKER_19]: Every neighborhood in the city is complaining.
[SPEAKER_19]: They have the exact same complaints as you.
[SPEAKER_19]: We have Yale Street, we have Albany Street, we have Fell's Ave,
[SPEAKER_19]: We have winter street, we have the whole Ram said road issue in the morning.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm sure that everybody would love to have a speed table on their street.
[SPEAKER_19]: I just don't know if it's feasible for the city to be able to do that.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's why I would defer to director Blake.
[SPEAKER_19]: He's the guy that knows where the resources are best allocated.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, this, this is one thing we strive to constantly improve the city and we have been very successful in getting grants to supplement our resources to try to continue to do things like this.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we seek opportunities when they present themselves as well, whether it's private or other.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, we, we will commit to continue to work the community to do, you know, every treatment we can within our resources and continue to add and incrementally improve.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, you know, that's, there are other streets that even want something like a radar feedback if they can't get a speed table and we, we even have to say no to them sometimes because we don't have enough to put around everywhere we want to put them.
[SPEAKER_33]: So but there is some light.
[SPEAKER_33]: At the end of the tunnel for this particular roadway segment because it was part of one of the recent grant applications.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, we did, we were able to accommodate Harvard app for instance recent, you know, in the past so many months with the radar feedback sign as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, hopefully these things will help Mr. Barry and his community, and we will continue more, but um yeah one one thing that's challenging for this commission is, it's not necessarily a commission that controls resources so even if they approve something.
[SPEAKER_33]: If there's no resources to do it is, it doesn't necessarily mean it's going to get done.
[SPEAKER_33]: And speed tables.
[SPEAKER_33]: There's some question if they're a gray area for traffic commission I've been not anyways just because it doesn't necessarily change the regulation, the speed limit is still 25 miles per hour in the city, a speed table just, you know, is a warning device that essentially gets people to conform to the 2025 versus going 40 or 3540.
[SPEAKER_33]: So, but we can look into other treatments.
[SPEAKER_33]: One thing I could ask you, Mr. Barry and others in the community.
[SPEAKER_33]: Do you have there any other situations in that neighborhood that we may not be aware of like a daycare use or anything that has what's considered to be vulnerable users.
[SPEAKER_33]: I know you mentioned the children but anything.
[SPEAKER_33]: that we may not be aware of, we may be missing.
[SPEAKER_33]: The reason why I mentioned that is because there is a tool at our disposal.
[SPEAKER_33]: Cities and towns don't control speed limits in their cities solely.
[SPEAKER_33]: The state has control over speed limits, but we do have some leeway for particular things to create safety zones that would lower speed limit from 25 to 20, but they require certain elements.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that's why I was inquiring about that.
[SPEAKER_33]: We can touch base offline to continue to work with you and your neighbors, see what's best for your quarter there.
[SPEAKER_33]: Great, thank you.
[SPEAKER_33]: Appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioners want to make a motion to approve or not approve this.
[SPEAKER_21]: I'd make a motion to deny but I hope Mr. Barry understands I think just because they're going to be other resources allocated there I'd like
[SPEAKER_21]: that to be put in place versus us committing to something which as Blake pointed out, may not be able, may not be feasible anyway, financially.
[SPEAKER_21]: So a motion to deny.
[SPEAKER_21]: Second.
[SPEAKER_22]: I'll vote.
[SPEAKER_21]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_21]: Do I vote in the affirmative or do I vote nay?
[SPEAKER_21]: I vote in support.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Hold on.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: There's a motion to approve.
[SPEAKER_19]: Let's make a motion to approve 2022-50.
[SPEAKER_19]: Right.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then you just don't approve it.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's how you die.
[SPEAKER_19]: Well, I don't think you have enough approval.
[SPEAKER_19]: You just deny it.
[SPEAKER_22]: He made a motion.
[SPEAKER_33]: All right, all right, all right.
[SPEAKER_33]: May make suggest you could, you could choose to, instead of deny or approve, you could choose to refer to, you know, DPW engineering to, to work on treatments, something like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: I don't know if that's an option.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm going to refer to engineering department.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah, that's a good option.
[SPEAKER_19]: You want to do motion to refer this to engineering?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is that gonna, Todd, is that gonna get us there if we refer it?
[SPEAKER_33]: I guess it leaves the door open if a pot of money fell in our laps that if you denied it and then we're restricted with the six month thing that was talked about earlier.
[SPEAKER_21]: I'd support that then.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's good, thank you, Todd.
[SPEAKER_19]: So do we get the motion to refer this to engineering for further study?
[SPEAKER_22]: I motion.
[SPEAKER_22]: No, Steve did.
[SPEAKER_22]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_21]: No, I motioned to deny.
[SPEAKER_21]: So I revoked that motion.
[SPEAKER_30]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_30]: I'll motion then.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioner Brzezinski makes a second.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'll second.
[SPEAKER_21]: Commissioner Pezzaturro.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pezzaturro?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_32]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGilvrey?
[SPEAKER_22]: Three in the affirmative, three to nothing, two absent.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion passes to be deferred.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, 2022-51, Joseph Camuso, Century Street.
[SPEAKER_19]: Extension to discuss the speed of traffic on this street and the possibility of a speed table.
[SPEAKER_19]: I see Mr. Camuso is present here.
[SPEAKER_12]: Yes, I am.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_12]: In my request, I actually said speed table, but in the long story,
[SPEAKER_12]: short of it, I live right next to Barry, I'm sorry, I say Barry Park, I grew up there, but I live right next to Placeton Park and from seven to nine and from say five to seven at night, we're just getting a lot of cars and they're actually coming from Mr. Barry's direction with good speed and Bustle Road is a little bit downhill.
[SPEAKER_12]: And even though there's a stop sign on Bustle, they get to come down our street.
[SPEAKER_12]: and go straight up all the way to the high school, so it's a straight shot.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I have some friends that use the Waze app, and when the train tracks are down in West Medford, they just go up Grove Street, over the speed table, right onto Bustle and straight down.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I'm not technically looking for a speed table, maybe a residence only during a certain time, or maybe step one of a longer step process.
[SPEAKER_12]: But I'd kind of like to hear what, maybe if you guys had some,
[SPEAKER_12]: some input or, you know, just to see what you guys might think to just to rectify this, because it's not just the children on the street.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's 99% of the children that are in the park.
[SPEAKER_12]: So it's not to keep children on our street safe.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's to keep children in the city safe through the flag football, the soccer and, you know, other people that use the park as well.
[SPEAKER_19]: Todd, did you want to make a comment?
[SPEAKER_19]: Directively?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: Can you hear me?
[SPEAKER_19]: You gotcha.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_33]: So yeah, I just pulled up Century Street extension.
[SPEAKER_33]: Just specify the obvious here.
[SPEAKER_33]: Mr. Barry if you're still on and others on.
[SPEAKER_33]: We're not necessarily going to treat century extension preferential to you.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's just there are certain criteria that some of these areas that's why I asked about the daycare.
[SPEAKER_33]: That may give us different opportunities, you know, not necessarily in terms of resources but in terms of ability to change things.
[SPEAKER_33]: So because this is next to a park in a playground area.
[SPEAKER_33]: We could do warning signage for that and do advisory speeds.
[SPEAKER_33]: But in addition to that, what I mentioned earlier what we have at our disposal is what's called a safety zone.
[SPEAKER_33]: So Medford citywide is 25 miles an hour speed limit, but cities and towns.
[SPEAKER_33]: using the MassDOT guidelines for speeding or speed regulations have the ability to drop the speed limit from 25 to 20 if they meet certain criteria.
[SPEAKER_33]: And this may be a stretch of a road that does meet that criteria.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that may be one additional element that we could pursue for this particular.
[SPEAKER_12]: My street is already lettered for 20 miles an hour.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I was dealing with Sergeant Rogers, who was very helpful with this situation.
[SPEAKER_12]: And they dropped the, it looks like a radar, you know, a tow behind unit, hoping that could give some, some, you know, feedback and some data on, you know, when is the volume of traffic coming down and when is the speed.
[SPEAKER_12]: ramping up, whether changing the direction of the street going from Placeden Road towards Bustle, and the end of Bustle, and on a separate note, the end of Bustle where Century Street meets Bustle, that's a really dark corner.
[SPEAKER_12]: A lot of overgrown trees, there's not houses on the train track side, so you're not getting any extra ambient light from stuff.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's just a really busy street, and I'm sure a few of my neighbors that are on might want to speak as well on their concerns as far as just to keep our kids safe and kids in the city as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: Sorry, one way is definitely an option to split a street one way one direction that helps sometimes, as long as you usually want to pair it with another one way if you do that.
[SPEAKER_33]: There are other things that have been out there in the past like the school texts on the ground the pavement markings, not school slow, things like that.
[SPEAKER_12]: So we could explore those options, not only talk, we have our four of those already on the street.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: The 20 mile per hour I will point out because in the past, we found that there are some that are out there that weren't necessarily officially approved meaning they're not legally binding so the 20, we might want to dot that I cross that T. They're actually hard science and there's about four of them that are that are installed on the park side of the street.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, the signs in the past have been put on different streets, locally through local approval but they require state approval as well.
[SPEAKER_33]: Even if there's a sign, I'm just saying, we could we could do that on our back end here, but uh, but yeah we'll, we'll definitely continue to investigate and try different things to help this community with, with the issues that they're that you're explaining.
[SPEAKER_12]: And just to make a statement, I live on the second house to the right of the street.
[SPEAKER_12]: So if they did make it a one way, I would have the second longest ride to go around.
[SPEAKER_12]: My house is the brick house with the black truck in front of it.
[SPEAKER_12]: And you can actually see that I already maintain like slow children signs out there.
[SPEAKER_12]: And it's just, it's not every car, it's one out of 20 that are going excessively fast.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I've looked into this a little bit and I've looked at some hot statistics and zero to 20, one out of 10 will perish.
[SPEAKER_12]: 0 to 30, 50% of people perish in an accident when it comes to a car and a pedestrian going head to head.
[SPEAKER_12]: And then as you go down to the end now as you're scrolling, that is the corner that is very, very difficult.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's a really dark corner.
[SPEAKER_12]: It's dangerous.
[SPEAKER_12]: That's another issue within itself.
[SPEAKER_12]: But if we just redirected traffic, possibly where you're at the backside of that car, we could put either residents only between a certain time
[SPEAKER_12]: You know, just something to kind of maybe just, just to redirect people.
[SPEAKER_12]: We're not looking to technically put our speed hump in, but you know, if all, if a couple of, you know, as a taxpayer, a couple of cheaper options might work.
[SPEAKER_33]: You just want traffic calming in general, whatever we can do to calm traffic.
[SPEAKER_12]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_33]: I will, I will say on behalf of the commission, or the city and then former commission meetings that do not have to accept residents are not enforceable so.
[SPEAKER_33]: In the past, so many traffic commissions, we've been staying away from that because they're just not enforceable.
[SPEAKER_33]: So we've leaned towards restrictions, turn restrictions that apply to everyone in some cases.
[SPEAKER_33]: But the one-way is intriguing.
[SPEAKER_33]: Usually there'd be a pair.
[SPEAKER_33]: So if Woods Road was amenable to a one-way pair with Century Street extension, that could be a viable option.
[SPEAKER_12]: I will say woods and Roberts are both two ways so if you did, she had the extra overflow of traffic so one wouldn't get the brunt of it.
[SPEAKER_12]: And again, I'm not no offense to the other residents on the other two streets but century Street extension has the park on it, woods road and Roberts road do not have a park on it.
[SPEAKER_33]: It looks like Roberts road is private as well.
[SPEAKER_12]: All three of these roads are private, but where I'm, I say, where me and my neighbors are on the park, it's really for the kids in the park.
[SPEAKER_12]: And I say that because I sit on my front steps and I see people drive fast.
[SPEAKER_12]: I've actually drove my truck down to the tennis courts and just sat there just to watch the speed of cars that are going down.
[SPEAKER_12]: And if any of the offices would like to speak, and I'm sure they understand that the cars are going, they're going excessive of 30, 33, 34 miles an hour on the regular.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I would just hope that they,
[SPEAKER_12]: just see what they could do as far as, I'm not saying I have the solution, but there's gotta be a solution or a happy medium for everyone, the neighbors on the street and the people that are using the park.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, I'd just like to say something real quick.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I speak for a moment?
[SPEAKER_17]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_05]: Hello?
[SPEAKER_17]: Yep, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I've been at 143 tennis courts for the last 20 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I can honestly say that I find no issue.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think the biggest issue on the street is the fact that people are trying to own the street that they don't own.
[SPEAKER_05]: For example, putting barrels outside and causing the biggest cause of traffic an issue on the street, because what they're doing is they're trying to redirect traffic on their own.
[SPEAKER_05]: and for some reason feel as if the street is owned by the people who are living on the street instead of the city.
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, there's speed everywhere.
[SPEAKER_05]: Putting a one-way is only going to manifest the situation because now there's no one coming the other way, and people are going to travel faster down the street.
[SPEAKER_05]: I faced a tennis courts, like I said, for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've never had an issue.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do people speed?
[SPEAKER_05]: They speed everywhere.
[SPEAKER_05]: But to say that there has been this bad of an issue to put a speed trap and all this other stuff is completely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I think that it should be open for the people to come in and out of the park with their families and their soccer families, instead of having all this stuff and driving around all this stuff that's left in the middle of the street to save a parking spot that has nothing to do with the traffic on the street.
[SPEAKER_05]: We could all put barrels out front of our house to save spaces, but it's not right.
[SPEAKER_05]: We bought our houses.
[SPEAKER_05]: on a park, and that's how it should remain.
[SPEAKER_05]: If anything, they should maybe put a police at the end of the street to direct those people and maybe slow down the people, give them a ticket.
[SPEAKER_05]: But this talk for a one-way street is absolutely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_05]: And speed bump and all this stuff is absolutely ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_05]: It should be a free street.
[SPEAKER_05]: The park has always been there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So I don't know why you know, all this is you know, I wasn't even notified of this meeting today No one even know I lived on the street for 20 years Why wasn't I notified that this was even on the agenda tonight is what I'd like to know We don't send out no but that that's already come up early we don't only certain people were notified I've been there for 20 years.
[SPEAKER_05]: I would think that I would be one of the first people to be notified
[SPEAKER_19]: Hold on, hold on.
[SPEAKER_19]: This came up, this came up earlier.
[SPEAKER_19]: The butters are not notified on agenda items.
[SPEAKER_19]: The petitioner is notified.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's why you weren't notified but the traffic commission agenda is posted on the city website for everybody to see.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, understood.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, hold on, hold on, hold on.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're not going to have an argument here.
[SPEAKER_19]: No, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_19]: We can have some that may disagree, agree, but we'll just keep it nice and calm and have a nice discussion.
[SPEAKER_33]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_33]: Somebody else want to speak on it I see Sergeant if I may, before we go too far into it.
[SPEAKER_33]: I should have mentioned this earlier and we should have vetted this before the traffic mission agenda was created century street extension is a private way for traffic commission does not have purview over it.
[SPEAKER_33]: All right.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, so I have one question to ask you.
[SPEAKER_05]: So is it a legal or illegal to put barrels in?
[SPEAKER_19]: You're muted.
[SPEAKER_19]: This is Pierro.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'm sorry, I'm just picking up my daughter from school.
[SPEAKER_05]: I said, I'm not sure what the laws are.
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it legal or illegal to obstruct traffic and put barrels and save spots out front of your house so other people don't park?
[SPEAKER_19]: There is no spot saving.
[SPEAKER_05]: Okay, so if that's the case, and this has been going on for years now, what do we do about that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it looks awful, and that's actually the real issue I feel on the street.
[SPEAKER_19]: Call the police.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's redirecting people.
[SPEAKER_05]: People are dodging.
[SPEAKER_33]: I would say since it's a private, since it's a private way, private, the owners of such private way could develop parking rules for their private way, according to our interpretation, the master law, we would direct anyone on a private way regarding parking to visit the city website.
[SPEAKER_33]: There's a, there's a page for information on parking on private ways.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it may become a moot point is what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: Todd, just one question.
[SPEAKER_21]: It's a private way.
[SPEAKER_21]: And we have no say.
[SPEAKER_21]: Is that correct?
[SPEAKER_21]: Tonight?
[SPEAKER_33]: Correct.
[SPEAKER_33]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_33]: We're not supposed to spend public money on private way.
[SPEAKER_33]: Um, if we do, there's a certain process, lengthy process that, yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: I mean, it sounds like an unfortunate situation, but if we don't have the purview to actually answer their problems, then, um, I think there's another forum for this group to, uh,
[SPEAKER_12]: to take their issues to sense myself and my other neighbors have waited two hours.
[SPEAKER_19]: You think my a couple of the other neighbors if they wanted to speak, we're gonna let them speak.
[SPEAKER_19]: So next up is Mr. Healy.
[SPEAKER_37]: Hi, yeah, so I'm in 151 also right across from the
[SPEAKER_37]: from the tennis courts.
[SPEAKER_37]: And I do have little kids who are two and five, and we do use the parks and we enjoy it a lot.
[SPEAKER_37]: And I would say that the direction coming from Bustle towards Playstead, because Century Street is the straight road and the flat road of the three of the private ways, gets the most traffic and gets the folks really whipping through the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_37]: Um, really fast.
[SPEAKER_37]: And, and, and that has, you know, luckily we haven't had an issue yet, but we've lived here for eight years and, um, it has been something, especially around high school time, you know, getting in, uh, in the mornings you get people whipping through at eight o'clock, uh, right.
[SPEAKER_37]: As I'm getting my kids into the car to get to school.
[SPEAKER_37]: So it's, it is a, uh,
[SPEAKER_37]: It is a busy spot, and we have noticed a lot of fast driving through the area.
[SPEAKER_37]: And I appreciate the trailer with the speed camera on it now, because that's helped people kind of realize what they're doing.
[SPEAKER_37]: But yeah, I'd like to see where this goes with Joe and what we can do as a community to help out on this.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Mike Casey?
[SPEAKER_19]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_02]: All right, hello.
[SPEAKER_02]: Thanks for giving us an opportunity to speak.
[SPEAKER_02]: So we live at 127 Century Street Extension for the past 15 years.
[SPEAKER_02]: We have an 11 year old, a nine year old and a seven year old.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there certainly has been moments of frogger watching them cross the street to get to the park as they've gotten older and are more free flow in their movements.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I think when we look at the main problem, it is speed coming around Bustle at the hours that everybody else has pointed out.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think Waze has created a situation where this has really become problematic in the last couple of years.
[SPEAKER_02]: So what may not have been a problem before has certainly become more of a problem over the last couple of years.
[SPEAKER_02]: I know when I walk my dog at seven in the morning, my son goes to middle school, he has to go around that corner at Bustle.
[SPEAKER_02]: So as already was said, coming down Grove, taking that turn on the Bustle, people fly.
[SPEAKER_02]: They don't stop at those stop signs, they continue down Bustle, and then they take that turn and they gun it going up Century Street Extension.
[SPEAKER_02]: Robert's Road, Woods Road have the luxury of having a huge dip in the middle of those two roads so the cars will bottom out if they go down those streets.
[SPEAKER_02]: Ours is nice and flat and straight, and it gives a nice straight run up to the high school so between seven and eight.
[SPEAKER_02]: The high schoolers that are coming around that corner, the parents driving the high schoolers, I know some of the parents.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's incredibly awkward when I give them the look like you're doing 30 miles an hour right in front of my house and my kids are going to school.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's, I think we need to focus on the fact that it is a speed problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: How do we mitigate the speed problem, whether or not
[SPEAKER_02]: It's a speed table looking at traffic direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think these all should be viable options on the table.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think it's disappointing to hear that you're saying, well, it's a private way, so we can't do anything.
[SPEAKER_02]: I think we need to address speed where we have young children, not only in the houses that abut the park, but I've watched kids run out in between cars to chase soccer balls.
[SPEAKER_02]: to chase their dog, whatever.
[SPEAKER_02]: And I don't think we want to wait until we have a tragedy placed at park before we agree that we need signs, speed tables and other mitigating things to help where the speed is basically the main problem.
[SPEAKER_02]: So I want to stay focused on that and make sure that we bring all of the solutions and then as a group, let's figure out the best way to address that.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, thank you very much.
[SPEAKER_19]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Lavoie?
[SPEAKER_19]: Hello, Jen LaVoy.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hi.
[SPEAKER_06]: Hey Pat LaVoy, one, two, three.
[SPEAKER_06]: I just think it's an overreaction.
[SPEAKER_06]: You know, I've been on the street, 50 years.
[SPEAKER_06]: Listen, safety first, I agree.
[SPEAKER_06]: It's all about the children, but I just think this is a real overreaction.
[SPEAKER_06]: Could we put a police officer down there maybe giving out tickets?
[SPEAKER_06]: I know 35 years ago, I got one on Placestead Road and it went a long way because every time I come down Placestead Road, it goes through my mind, getting that ticket years ago.
[SPEAKER_06]: It goes a long way, a ticket.
[SPEAKER_06]: So, I mean, it would be great to have a police officer down there, you know, slowing things down for a while.
[SPEAKER_06]: And as far as the one way off the table for me, speed bump off the table for me, I totally oppose it.
[SPEAKER_06]: I'd like to see what the data is from the
[SPEAKER_06]: from the radar that was put out there.
[SPEAKER_06]: Are we really that out of control?
[SPEAKER_06]: I don't think so.
[SPEAKER_06]: But that's my two cents.
[SPEAKER_31]: I appreciate that.
[SPEAKER_31]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_31]: Go ahead, ma'am.
[SPEAKER_40]: I'm going to add my two cents as well.
[SPEAKER_40]: So I'm Jen Lavoie at the same street.
[SPEAKER_40]: So we got this notice the other night from one of the neighbors.
[SPEAKER_40]: And when I looked at it, I hadn't noticed any significant uptick in traffic or speeding on the street.
[SPEAKER_40]: So I was a little bit concerned or not sure what the issue was.
[SPEAKER_40]: So yesterday and today,
[SPEAKER_40]: As I've been home, I've sat outside my house and counted the number of cars that have gone by at different times.
[SPEAKER_40]: This morning from 8 to 8.35, we had seven cars go by.
[SPEAKER_40]: Two of them were neighbors, a neighbor who went out to get coffee and came back.
[SPEAKER_40]: So we are averaging one car every five minutes on the street.
[SPEAKER_40]: I'm not talking multiple cars, I'm talking one car goes by.
[SPEAKER_40]: In terms of the ways redirecting traffic,
[SPEAKER_40]: I mean, everybody loves a shortcut, right?
[SPEAKER_40]: I take shortcuts.
[SPEAKER_40]: I'm sure everyone on the street will take a shortcut if they can.
[SPEAKER_40]: It's temporary.
[SPEAKER_40]: Maybe they send a few cars down the street.
[SPEAKER_40]: Once the train's gone, the issue is over.
[SPEAKER_40]: I don't see a huge, significant uptick in speeding or traffic.
[SPEAKER_40]: I've watched the radar trailer.
[SPEAKER_40]: The fastest I saw somebody go is the postal truck.
[SPEAKER_40]: He went 27 miles.
[SPEAKER_40]: per hour today.
[SPEAKER_40]: Is there any data from that trailer being there?
[SPEAKER_40]: I'd be really curious to know if it measures speed, if it measures volume.
[SPEAKER_40]: I had more walkers on my street this morning than cars.
[SPEAKER_40]: I had people walking dogs.
[SPEAKER_40]: I had people with children walking.
[SPEAKER_40]: I had runners.
[SPEAKER_40]: I had
[SPEAKER_40]: you know, more pedestrians, they're not walking on the sidewalk, they're walking in the street.
[SPEAKER_40]: If it was such a dangerous street, wouldn't they all be on the sidewalk?
[SPEAKER_40]: I walk my grandson on the street, not on the sidewalk.
[SPEAKER_40]: I don't see what the significant issue is.
[SPEAKER_19]: So those trailers do collect data.
[SPEAKER_19]: Those trailers are older.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're in the process of getting new trailers that we can actually get the data right here at the police station through the cloud.
[SPEAKER_19]: We have a thumb drive in that trailer.
[SPEAKER_19]: When we retrieve that trailer, we will download the thumb drive when we hope that we'll be able to retrieve the data.
[SPEAKER_19]: But like I said, those trailers are 10 years old.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're in the process of buying new trailers.
[SPEAKER_19]: Does anybody else have anything to say about this situation?
[SPEAKER_19]: Because like Director Blake said, this is a private way.
[SPEAKER_19]: I live in a private way in that neighborhood also, so I get it.
[SPEAKER_19]: We have to look at private ways a little differently when it comes to repairs.
[SPEAKER_19]: But I did want to give everybody an opportunity to speak.
[SPEAKER_19]: I hope that the neighborhood can come together and figure out an amicable way to resolve this.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll certainly be down there doing everything we can to alleviate the situation.
[SPEAKER_19]: I can say that we deal with this issue in every neighborhood in the city.
[SPEAKER_19]: Every neighborhood has the same complaints and we're doing the best we can.
[SPEAKER_19]: I wish we had a hundred police officers on the day shift to go in and take care of all these problems, but we don't.
[SPEAKER_19]: So we're doing the best we can.
[SPEAKER_19]: Does anybody else, I don't want to deprive anybody an opportunity to speak.
[SPEAKER_19]: Does anybody else want to speak?
[SPEAKER_33]: Okay, just just one more quick thing in the private way.
[SPEAKER_33]: It is a private way but the unusual case in this particular case, the city is in a butter to that private way.
[SPEAKER_33]: So even if we don't own the street where we're one half of the butters right so we'll check with legal to see what what that until if that gives us it sounds like this, the risk was the commercial you did say that the city has put the slow signs and everything down there.
[SPEAKER_19]: I drive down that street all the time myself, I just can't.
[SPEAKER_12]: They're actually faded now and I actually called Mrs. Menezes.
[SPEAKER_12]: I forget what department she's in.
[SPEAKER_12]: And she said that, you know, if I call back, maybe we can get them repainted from the ground.
[SPEAKER_12]: And there's a bunch that were put up by the city.
[SPEAKER_12]: Possibly I moved in in 2013.
[SPEAKER_12]: I bought the house from my grandmother and I lived with her after I lost my parents.
[SPEAKER_12]: So I've been on the street for a long time as well.
[SPEAKER_12]: I would say about eight, seven, eight years ago, those signs went up.
[SPEAKER_12]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can I say one thing?
[SPEAKER_05]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_05]: One question is, is I don't think half of those signs around the street are actually signs that the city put up.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the slow sign that's spray painted at the end of my street was hand painted at the end of the street.
[SPEAKER_05]: And I'd like that to be looked into because I think someone actually spray painted the street and put slow there.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, we will, myself and Sergeant Rogers.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, because it doesn't look like an official,
[SPEAKER_19]: Myself, Sergeant Rogers and Director Blake, we'll look at all the signage down there.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll look at all the paintings on the roadway.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll make sure that everything conforms to what it's supposed to conform to.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll take care of that in the next week.
[SPEAKER_19]: But we do have the- Can I speak?
[SPEAKER_19]: Go ahead.
[SPEAKER_06]: Yeah, so as far as the signage, we have five unofficial no parking signs.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have three no loitering, three no after dock parking.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have an orange construction barrel.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have no rollerblading, no stick ball, no street hockey, tennis only, and an official police horse.
[SPEAKER_06]: We have 20 signs and that's at a minimum.
[SPEAKER_06]: I didn't count them all.
[SPEAKER_06]: Enough with the signs.
[SPEAKER_06]: Listen, we should be a welcoming park.
[SPEAKER_06]: Okay, we're making it difficult for families to come down and to park.
[SPEAKER_06]: They have enough on their hands to get their children across the street without us taking parking spots away from them.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't want to cut anybody short.
[SPEAKER_19]: I see Chris Lavoie has his hand up.
[SPEAKER_19]: Did you want to say something?
[SPEAKER_19]: Sorry, I got on mute.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm sorry.
[SPEAKER_11]: Mr. Lavoie.
[SPEAKER_11]: There we go.
[SPEAKER_11]: Can you hear me now?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay, thank you.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I have to apologize.
[SPEAKER_11]: I've lost track of what is or is not on the table in terms of- I can read it.
[SPEAKER_19]: I can read it.
[SPEAKER_19]: So there's a request from Joe Camuso, Century Street Extension, to discuss speed of traffic on the street and the possibility of a speed table.
[SPEAKER_19]: And then the issue that it's a private way was addressed.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're giving the neighborhood an opportunity to speak,
[SPEAKER_19]: We do need to move on because we have to take a vote on this, but go ahead.
[SPEAKER_11]: So I guess in terms of any enforcement, I want to voice my opinion.
[SPEAKER_11]: I am 100% not in favor of a one way.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think that that only adds to congestion issues in the neighborhood.
[SPEAKER_11]: Again, I think to the points that have been made here, we already have the trailer out there.
[SPEAKER_11]: Facts are our friends.
[SPEAKER_11]: So let's let the data inform our response.
[SPEAKER_11]: I think we should look at hard numbers before we really try to put a permanent measure in place.
[SPEAKER_11]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_11]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm going to go to the commissioners.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion to vote on this agenda item.
[SPEAKER_33]: two dash 51 sorry if this is a private way I wonder if we even have a jurisdiction if you should consider referring it to legal to to inquire if you have purview or not so we need a motion for that to defer this to the city solicitor for further motion to refer to legal for further input on whether we have rights to review and approve
[SPEAKER_19]: Second.
[SPEAKER_22]: Second.
[SPEAKER_19]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Passatoro.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGillivray.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Three in the affirmative, two absent, no negative.
[SPEAKER_19]: The motion will be deferred to legal.
[SPEAKER_19]: In the interim, we will be down there to look at the signage and we will
[SPEAKER_19]: do our best to conduct more enforcement down in that area.
[SPEAKER_19]: We'll download these.
[SPEAKER_19]: We will also be looking at the speed drill in the near future.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, thank you everybody for your patience tonight.
[SPEAKER_19]: 2022-52, request from Bill Powell, 67 Almond Street, for no parking here to corner on Almond Street at the corner of Almond Court.
[SPEAKER_19]: Todd, can you just pull that up on Google Maps just so we have it?
[SPEAKER_19]: Is the petitioner here?
[SPEAKER_19]: Bill Powers?
[SPEAKER_20]: Not here?
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant, I went down there.
[SPEAKER_20]: As we know, I'm on Streets and Narrow Street.
[SPEAKER_20]: I can see Mr. Powers' concern coming out of, and I hope this is what he's talking about, coming out of Elmont Court, turning left on Elmont Street.
[SPEAKER_31]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's a narrow street.
[SPEAKER_19]: It'd be very tough.
[SPEAKER_19]: So again, this is another situation where we have the automatic 20 feet corner.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do we want to do a similar situation where we vote on this motion where we pass it and refer it to the fire department for further review?
[SPEAKER_19]: I just pass it.
[SPEAKER_33]: Sergeant if I may.
[SPEAKER_33]: Okay, go ahead.
[SPEAKER_33]: So I wonder if the confusion with this particular one is that it is a street.
[SPEAKER_33]: However, it's designed, it looks like a driveway.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that may be why people aren't obeying a 20 foot from an intersection because it appears to be a driveway.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it may help clarify if there was a sign 20 feet from either side, or whatever feet the traffic commission deems necessary.
[SPEAKER_33]: But if it's a driveway, it's a two to three foot rule.
[SPEAKER_33]: If it's in section 20, it's a street.
[SPEAKER_33]: So it probably should be the 20, but that's probably why there's people parking very close to it, is my guess.
[SPEAKER_19]: Great point, Todd.
[SPEAKER_20]: I absolutely see that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_20]: Todd, what about if you put two signs, no parking between signs?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, I like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: It's just a matter of do we go straight with the 20 because in a street, or do we do some, you know, adjustments that is, I guess the only question, I like the idea of the two signs one here and one here and there, no parking between the signs, just a matter of where exactly to put them to be reasonable with access and parking and all that.
[SPEAKER_20]: Like you said no 20 feet and intersection, there really isn't an intersection, the way it looks like a driveway.
[SPEAKER_33]: So I don't know if the commission were to like, because the unusual circumstance do you do somewhere between the two and three of a driveway that's 20 of an intersection, or do you just go with the standard 20.
[SPEAKER_33]: I'm not sure myself, but seems like somewhere in the middle of those two make sense.
[SPEAKER_19]: Standard 20 is easy to enforce correct.
[SPEAKER_19]: You just put the sign up and it's enforceable.
[SPEAKER_19]: And it's a one-way, is it a one-way street?
[SPEAKER_19]: It's a one-way street.
[SPEAKER_19]: So going the other way doesn't really matter, it's just- It'd be almost put a sign in front of those stairs.
[SPEAKER_19]: Taking the right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Taking the left.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is it a left?
[SPEAKER_19]: Left.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'm looking at around the... What are we looking at, El Moncorte there?
[SPEAKER_19]: El Moncorte.
[SPEAKER_19]: So it's a one-way going out to what?
[SPEAKER_33]: El Moncorte's a dead end, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_19]: Elmont Court's a two-way.
[SPEAKER_19]: Elmont Street is, does it go one way to the Fells Way or to Salem Street?
[SPEAKER_19]: The other way to Salem.
[SPEAKER_19]: Fells Way to Salem Street?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yep.
[SPEAKER_19]: So if you're taking, if you're coming out, it's a left, right?
[SPEAKER_19]: If he's coming out at Elmont Court, you gotta go left.
[SPEAKER_20]: You gotta go left, yeah.
[SPEAKER_20]: And he wants to know, so you can make, it is a tough turn.
[SPEAKER_20]: Coming out of Elmont Court, turning left on Elmont Street.
[SPEAKER_39]: 20 feet.
[SPEAKER_20]: But if people aren't seeing it as an intersection.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yeah, looks like a driveway.
[SPEAKER_20]: Literally looks like a driveway.
[SPEAKER_20]: Yeah, no, I see that.
[SPEAKER_22]: No parking between signs.
[SPEAKER_20]: I said between signs.
[SPEAKER_21]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_21]: I mean, shouldn't we just treat it like an intersection?
[SPEAKER_21]: I know it doesn't look like an intersection, but I'd much rather put up a sign that makes it more look like an intersection than no parking between the signs.
[SPEAKER_33]: I kind of I kind of, I'm thinking on those lines to it's yeah so I mean this 20 foot rule would be if these are roughly four to five feet 1234 so it would probably be either here here with, but you don't need one day right, Todd, because this is one way.
[SPEAKER_33]: Well, I mean, the 20 foot rule is all corners and then also, if people are turning left, they're looking right so a car parked here could block the view of the view.
[SPEAKER_30]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: So if you treat, I mean, if you treat it as a standard intersection would be 20 feet this way 20 feet that way 20 feet that way 20 feet that way.
[SPEAKER_33]: I mean this.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: So 20 feet would roughly be 1234 somewhere either here or here if they're four feet is here if they're five feet is here.
[SPEAKER_33]: And then on this side.
[SPEAKER_33]: 1234 probably to the stairwell.
[SPEAKER_21]: We'd have to put up two signs anyway correct if you put no parking between the signs or you put no, no parking from here to the corner.
[SPEAKER_21]: I think I'd much rather vote on something that makes it
[SPEAKER_21]: even though it doesn't appear optically like an intersection I think I'd much rather put the signs up that didn't know that it is a, in fact, an intersection.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, so you're suggesting signing needs to put two signs up parking.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, no parking here two corners, I guess what you're saying versus between right.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_31]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_30]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_30]: That was good.
[SPEAKER_19]: Does that have to be amended.
[SPEAKER_30]: No.
[SPEAKER_21]: So we can just because it says.
[SPEAKER_21]: He's not looking for more than 20 feet.
[SPEAKER_21]: Nope, he's not.
[SPEAKER_21]: Petitioner.
[SPEAKER_22]: He was actually looking for less than 20.
[SPEAKER_19]: He's only looking for one sign.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do we have to amend that for the second sign or can we just vote on it?
[SPEAKER_22]: No, you can add both corners.
[SPEAKER_22]: Refer it to the highway department?
[SPEAKER_22]: Nope, you can, both, even though he only requests for one corner, you can, the traffic commission can pass.
[SPEAKER_22]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's both corners.
[SPEAKER_19]: Just on this, without changing the language.
[SPEAKER_19]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, motion to vote on that.
[SPEAKER_19]: on that agenda item.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second.
[SPEAKER_22]: I'll second.
[SPEAKER_19]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastoraccio.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Regent McGilvray.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Reading nothing, two absent.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, one last item, last agenda item.
[SPEAKER_19]: And I apologize for the wait, Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Lima.
[SPEAKER_19]: 2022-53 Handicap Park and sign Catherine Lima, 79 Dexter Street.
[SPEAKER_24]: Hi, yes, I'm here.
[SPEAKER_24]: Can you hear me?
[SPEAKER_19]: Patiently waiting, yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: We apologize for the wait.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you for your patience.
[SPEAKER_24]: I was warned that it would be long, so I was prepared.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you.
[SPEAKER_24]: So I'm basically requesting that a Handicap Park sign be put out in front of my home because
[SPEAKER_24]: I unfortunately have had to have both my hips replaced.
[SPEAKER_24]: I need both my knees replaced.
[SPEAKER_24]: And we're trying to push that off as long as possible, which is what my orthopedist recommended.
[SPEAKER_24]: We have a lot of cars on the street.
[SPEAKER_24]: The house next to us is all roommates.
[SPEAKER_24]: They have multiple cars.
[SPEAKER_24]: Sometimes it's very difficult for me to even find parking on the street, nevermind get to where I need to go.
[SPEAKER_20]: Sergeant Rogers?
[SPEAKER_20]: I went down there, Sergeant.
[SPEAKER_20]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_20]: Lynn was not home at the time when I went down there.
[SPEAKER_20]: It is almost right at the bend on Daxter Street, and I would move for approval.
[SPEAKER_19]: Commissioners, do you need Mr. Blake to bring it up on Google Maps, or do you want to just take the motion as it is?
[SPEAKER_31]: No.
[SPEAKER_24]: I just have one comment.
[SPEAKER_24]: So where the children's sign is now, apparently my landlord had said that that's where handicap parking sign was before.
[SPEAKER_24]: I didn't know if that's where it would be or not because the space is further down or actually blocked by trees.
[SPEAKER_19]: We could pull it up.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you, Director Blake.
[SPEAKER_19]: Highway can move the signs around as they see appropriate.
[SPEAKER_32]: Is there a request here or here?
[SPEAKER_21]: It's probably a question for Tim that we can make that pole taller and then it would accommodate both sides, correct?
[SPEAKER_21]: I think the problems are pretty.
[SPEAKER_33]: If they wanted this pole, we could swap it out and move this elsewhere potentially.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do that too.
[SPEAKER_19]: That's probably the best solution.
[SPEAKER_21]: Just one question for the record, the driveway is not accessible.
[SPEAKER_24]: The landlord uses the driveway, I have no access to it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay, very good.
[SPEAKER_19]: I just need to make sure that the paperwork is in order from Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Erickson.
[SPEAKER_19]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Erickson, is the paperwork in order?
[SPEAKER_22]: We have a question.
[SPEAKER_19]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Lima, did you recently move here?
[SPEAKER_24]: So it's been a year, I do need to update the registration on my,
[SPEAKER_24]: on my thing, and I do have it written on the back of my license, but I can certainly do that if need be.
[SPEAKER_19]: I think maybe we should wait till the next meeting when the registration is updated.
[SPEAKER_19]: Do I have a motion to table?
[SPEAKER_19]: No, you can't, it's six months.
[SPEAKER_19]: I'll table.
[SPEAKER_19]: Hold on, hold on.
[SPEAKER_19]: You can't bring it up again for six months if we table it?
[SPEAKER_32]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_32]: Yeah, you can.
[SPEAKER_32]: No, next meeting.
[SPEAKER_19]: Next meeting.
[SPEAKER_19]: If we deny it, it's six months.
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: So motion to table.
[SPEAKER_19]: Ms.
[SPEAKER_19]: Lemer, I apologize.
[SPEAKER_19]: I know you waited a long time.
[SPEAKER_19]: I apologize, but we do need the registration to reflect that the vehicle's coming out of that address.
[SPEAKER_24]: Okay, I completely understand.
[SPEAKER_24]: So I can certainly do that and then I'll send it over to you guys and then I would be on the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_24]: Is that correct?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_24]: And then is it in the beginning of the month like this one was?
[SPEAKER_19]: The second Tuesday.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second Tuesday of the month.
[SPEAKER_19]: I believe the 12th, 13th.
[SPEAKER_22]: If you get it updated, send it to me as soon as possible, and we can see if we can do a conference call to bring it forward before the meeting.
[SPEAKER_22]: If not, it will be at the October meeting.
[SPEAKER_19]: October 11th.
[SPEAKER_24]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: I have a motion by Commissioner Brzezinski to table it.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second by Commissioner Passatoro.
[SPEAKER_19]: Roll call vote.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Pastororo?
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGilvray?
[SPEAKER_19]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Seeing nothing, two absent.
[SPEAKER_19]: Motion will be tabled for the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_19]: I don't have any other current agenda items.
[SPEAKER_19]: Is there anybody?
[SPEAKER_19]: Melissa Hall, did you want to speak on something?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, I do have a question.
[SPEAKER_07]: I did submit a petition at the end of last week.
[SPEAKER_07]: I did come a little late to the meeting because of work, but I've been on the meeting for about two hours now, and I don't believe it came up.
[SPEAKER_07]: Was there a petition in that pile with my name on it?
[SPEAKER_22]: No.
[SPEAKER_22]: Her petition... What was the petition for, ma'am?
[SPEAKER_07]: So I've been living on 262 Main Street for the last three years with two of my roommates.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I know with a new T stop there, they're looking to expand the resident permit parking into the transit district B area to have that whole area be resident permit parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: But I know my roommates and I very specifically chose the street that we live on because it's non-resident parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: because for one R doesn't have a driveway that we would have access to.
[SPEAKER_07]: I know a lot of homes on Main Street don't have driveways just because it's a very busy street.
[SPEAKER_07]: A lot of the side streets are already permit parking and have driveways, but Main Street has been non-permit.
[SPEAKER_07]: And then on top of that, between, it's not gonna be permit?
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's not gonna be permit parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: Correct perfect that really such an anxiety, like, I don't know how many work.
[SPEAKER_33]: This is this is regarding the previous agenda item to know you know what that yeah this goes to 2022 was tabled but but if it, if it does eventually come before to get through, not going to be affected me know main street in the red areas.
[SPEAKER_33]: If that goes forward and is proved that will be part of it.
[SPEAKER_22]: It is.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yeah, it is.
[SPEAKER_19]: We're going to permit parking on Main Street.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah, is there a that's why I wanted to address it is there a way for like those common arteries within that transit be to remain non permit parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: because otherwise it's the entirety of South Medford that's gonna be resident permit parking.
[SPEAKER_07]: And I know that the whole purpose of this is to prevent commuters from parking and accessing the T for their daily commute.
[SPEAKER_07]: However, there are some people who live in the area that use that for very specific reasons who don't have driveways who might not be able to obtain a resident permit sticker for one reason or another.
[SPEAKER_07]: So,
[SPEAKER_19]: Yeah, that was my question I know it says mistake, obtain but that's not really a parking zone to get the good news is it was tabled and you'll have an opportunity to speak at the next.
[SPEAKER_19]: The next meeting.
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_33]: To be accommodating to businesses and other needs like that on major arteries, there is the two hour 8am to 8pm piece, which is very common in other communities, such as the neighboring community of Somerville on streets like Broadway, Highland Ave, things like that.
[SPEAKER_33]: So that's kind of the model we were taking after where it would be two hour, 8am to 8pm.
[SPEAKER_33]: It wouldn't affect overnight per se just permit overnight, some sections would have permit overnight the sections along the along the residential uses.
[SPEAKER_33]: But that's what's being presented it was tabled so.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: I'll, I'll definitely try to make the next meeting.
[SPEAKER_07]: Is there like, is this conversation now going to be of noted that it's a petition to just keep main street the same as it is, um, as it's a main artery and use for multiple uses without implementing any sort of permit parking.
[SPEAKER_19]: What you're going to have to do was appear at the next meeting and oppose the agenda item.
[SPEAKER_19]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_19]: It's not gonna be a separate petition, correct, Todd?
[SPEAKER_33]: Yeah, I would suggest, in addition to what Sergeant just recommended, you could also, anyone on this call or watching on TV, could submit a letter, email, if you can't attend as well.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, I did submit a letter via email, a petition for this meeting.
[SPEAKER_07]: It wasn't received.
[SPEAKER_07]: I sent it to Traffic Commissioner Erickson's email, I believe.
[SPEAKER_19]: We have it on record.
[SPEAKER_19]: We do have it on.
[SPEAKER_07]: Oh, you do.
[SPEAKER_07]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_07]: Perfect.
[SPEAKER_07]: Um, and I'm going to try to make next meeting, but I'm a nurse.
[SPEAKER_07]: So my schedule is all over the place, which is why another reason I'm concerned about, cause I'm not always working during the day.
[SPEAKER_07]: Sometimes I'm working at night.
[SPEAKER_07]: So sometimes I'm parked during the day.
[SPEAKER_07]: So those two hours, even though that's traditional work hours for most, um, you know, it's not for all like, because I can work overnights.
[SPEAKER_07]: I might have to, you know,
[SPEAKER_07]: I don't have a driveway or parking where I could avoid that resident permit sticker.
[SPEAKER_19]: Sort of like a police officer, we get it.
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes, yes, it's causing a lot of anxiety to me and my roommates right now, I'm pretty sure.
[SPEAKER_07]: All right, well, thank you for your time.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right, that's all we have, motion to adjourn?
[SPEAKER_07]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_19]: Second?
[SPEAKER_19]: Second.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right, roll call.
[SPEAKER_22]: Commissioner Brzezinski?
[SPEAKER_21]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_22]: Sergeant McGilvary.
[SPEAKER_22]: Nothing too absent.
[SPEAKER_22]: Meeting is adjourned.
[SPEAKER_22]: 8.13 PM.
[SPEAKER_19]: Thank you everybody for your patience.
[SPEAKER_33]: For the record, I predicted 8.30.
[SPEAKER_19]: If the chief was still sitting in this chair, it would have been 8.30.
[SPEAKER_19]: All right.
[SPEAKER_19]: Have a good night, everybody.